<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option A.
The Question Type given is Type D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option D.
All the continuous chemical reactions in the
bodies of living organisms that gave rise to
energy changes in their bodies are termed
metabolism. Metabolism consists of two
processes viz:
a) anabolism
b) catabolism
Anabolism is the synthesis or building up of
a complex body substance from simpler
constituents and energy.
Catabolism is the decomposition or
breaking down of a complex substance
resulting in the liberation of simpler
substances and energy.
Tropism, on the other hand, is a type of
response movement in which part(s) of a
plant moves in response to a directional
stimulus.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option B.
One of the animal characteristics of euglena
is the possession of eye spot or
photoreceptor which is sensitive to light.
The gullet is for ingestion and acts as a
reservoir. Flagellum is for movement and
the presence of chloroplast is one of the
characteristics of a plant. Chloroplast
contains chlorophyll which is used for
photosynthesis.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option B.
Cellular respiration leading to the
production of energy occurs in the
mitochondria while chloroplast contains
chlorophyll which is used for
photosynthesis. Hence, cells that are
actively respiring and photosynthesizing will
contain mitochondria and chloroplast.
The nucleus controls the activity of the cell;
lysosomes contain digestive enzymes;
ribosomes are sites for protein synthesis.
Endoplasmic aids the transport of materials
within the cytoplasm; golgi apparatus or
bodies function in synthesis, packaging and
distribution of materials and centrioles are
important in cell division.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option B.
Taenia solium or pork tapeworm has man
as its primary host and pig as its secondary
host.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option D.
Tapeworms are found in moist soil rich in
humus.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option B.
Arthropods have exoskeleton made of
chitin. They possess segmented body with
jointed appendages but the appendages are
not just a pair. In crustacea, the thoracic
segments bear eight pairs of appendages;
arachnida have four pairs of jointed legs;
myriapods have many walking legs that are
jointed and insects have three pairs of
jointed legs and a pair of jointed antennae.
Growth is not easy as they have to shed
their skeleton at intervals to allow for
growth. This is called moulting or ecdysis.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B.
Butterflies and moths both possess a pair of
wings; while butterflies are diurnal insects,
most moths are nocturnal. They differ from
butterflies as they have fatter and more
hairy bodies. The antennae of most moths
are pointed at their tips while those of most
butterflies have knobs at their tips. At rest,
the wings of most moths are spread out
horizontally while those of most butterflies
are held vertically. The fore and hind wings
of a moth are connected to each other
while those of a butterfly are not. The
pupae of a moth are generally enclosed in
well-developed cocoons while those of
butterflies are not. Most butterflies are
bright-coloured while moths tend to have
dull colouring.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option C.
Quill feathers (flight feathers) are used for
flying; they are large and stiff; they occur on
the tail and wing. Filoplumes are small hairlike
feathers; they are sparsely distributed
over the body and grow in clusters. Covert
feathers are for insulation. They make a
44
warm, light covering for the bird’s body
especially on the breast. Down feathers are
also for insulation; they grow beneath the
quill and covert feathers; they are soft and
fluffy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option B.
Xerophytes are plants that can survive in
places where water supply is limited, either
because there is little of it in deserts or
conditions make it difficult for the root to
absorb water e.g. high mountain tops.
Variety of adaptations shown by xerophytes
which enable them to live in such
conditions are termed xeromorphic
features.
Mesophytes are plants which live in places
where conditions are neither extremely wet
nor extremely dry.
Hydrophytes are plants that live in water or
extremely wet environment.
Epiphytes are plants that live on the trunk
of other plants, only for support and not for
nutritive purpose; hence, they are nonparasitic
plants.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option D.
Viruses which cannot reproduce
independently are smaller and simpler than
bacteria and much simpler than protozoans
like amoeba, paramecium and
chlamydomonas. However, which microbe
is the simplest organism depends on our
definitions of living organisms; outside
other living cells, viruses are non-living, if
excluded, the simplest free-living organism
is mycoplasma genitallum – a living parasitic
bacteria that lives in the digestive and
genital tracts of primates.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option C.
All insects have basic mouthparts which are
modified according to the food they eat.
The mouthpart consist of the mandible,
maxilla, labrum, labium, hypopharynx,
maxillary and labial palp. In butterfly, the
maxillae are modified into a long proboscis
for sucking up liquid. In mosquitoes, the
proboscis consists of four long sharp stylets,
modified from the mandibles and maxillae.
In housefly, the proboscis is formed from a
modified labium. Tapeworms, amphibians
and mollusks lack proboscis.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option A.
Desert plants lack broad leaves, with
numerous stomata as this will lead to high
transpiration of water. Spongyl mesophyll is
part of the internal structure of a leaf.
Prominent stomata in leaves will make
more water to be released to the
atmosphere as desert plants need to
conserve water, their leaves are reduced to
spine to reduce the surface area from which
water can leave the plants to the
atmosphere.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option B.
Birds like weavers have strong, short and
conical beak to pick and crack or crush
seeds. Those that feed on edible things in
muddy waters like flamingo have
boomerang-shaped beak with slits for
scooping mud and sieving it for food. Birds
that feed on flesh like hawk and owl have
strong and hooked beak for tearing flesh
and strong, long sharp and curved clawed
feet for grasping prey.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option C.
Chemosynthetic organisms are capable of
manufacturing their own food from simple
inorganic substances such as carbon (IV)
oxide, water and hydrogen sulphide using
the energy released during chemical
reactions and not sunlight energy. Examples
are sulphur bacteria which can oxidize
hydrogen sulphide around it to produce
energy; nitrifying bacteria (nitrosomonas
and nitrobacter) which oxidize ammonia to
nitrites and nitrates respectively.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option C.
Osmosis has to do with the movement of
solvents (water); during diffusion,
molecules move from one region to another
depending on their concentration gradients.
Transpiration is the movement of excess
water in form of water vapour out of the
aerial parts of a plant to the atmosphere.
Translocation is the movement of
manufactured food consisting of minerals
and chemical compounds from the leaf to
45
other parts of the plant through the
phloem.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option B.
The enzyme present in saliva which works
on starch is ptyalin. Pepsin and rennin are
present in the stomach while lipase works
on lipids; it is present in the duodenum and
ileum.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option C.
Carnivorous plants are plants that feed on
insects or other tiny animal to supplement
their nitrogenous intake by trapping and
absorbing mechanisms. Examples are
sundew of the genus drosera, bladderwort
of the genus utricularia, venus fly trap and
pitcher plant.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option D.
Heterotrophs are organisms that cannot
manufacture their food by themselves.
Fungi lack chlorophyll; hence, they cannot
photosynthesize. They feed saprophytically.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D.
Parasites are organisms that live on another
organism called the host; they depend
partially or wholly on them. Plasmodium is
a parasitic protozoon; it lives inside human
blood causing a disease called malaria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option D.
Leucocytes or white blood cells are divided
into two groups based on their structures.
They are follows:
(i) The mononuclears or agranulocytes.
(ii) The polymorphonuclears or
granulocytes.
Agranulocytes are white blood cells with
clear cytoplasm and an oval or bean-shaped
nucleus. Granulocytes are with granular
cytoplasm with lobed nucleus.
Agranulocytes are of two varieties namely
the lymphocyte and the monocyte.
Lymphocytes are concerned with the
production of anti-bodies and anti-toxins
both of which protect the body from the
harmful effect of disease-causing organisms
i.e., they give immunity against diseases;
therefore, they constitute the immune
system of the body. Monocytes are
phagocytic in function; they ingest and
destroy harmful micro-organisms that enter
the blood. Erythrocytes are red blood cells;
they help in the transportation oxygen
round the body.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option C.
The blood circulatory system of vertebrates
is made up of the heart and blood vessels –
arteries, veins and capillaries.
Aorta is the main artery in the body that
moves oxygenated blood away from the
heart; outside the heart is differentiated
into other arteries that move oxygenated
blood to different and specific organs in the
body. The vena cava is the main vein; there
are other veins that carry deoxygenated
blood from body organs to the vena-cavae
before they take it to the heart.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D.
The xylem carries water and mineral salts
from the root to other parts of the plant.
Phloem carries manufactured food from the
leaf to other parts of the plant. Cambium is
a merismatic tissue; it is responsible for
secondary growth in dicot plants. Cortex is
the tissue which lies between the epidermis
and the stele of a stem or a root or the
outer part of an organ such as the kidney or
the adrenal gland.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option B
Blood clotting or coagulation is an
important process that prevents excessive
bleeding when blood vessels are injured.
The process involves platelets and blood
proteins. Platelets plugs are formed due to
exposure of damaged blood vessels to air.
The platelets release a chemical, which
causes involuntary muscles in the walls of
the damaged blood vessels to constrict and
so reducing blood flow, that releases an
enzyme called thrombokinase or thrombo
plastin, which converts inactive prothombin
into an active enzyme called thrombin, this
in the presence of Ca2+ converts fibrinogen,
a blood protein into fibrin. The fibrin forms
a mesh of fine thread that traps blood cells
forming a clot that covers the wound.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option A
46
Blood plasma is the straw coloured pale
yellow liquid component of blood that
normally holds the blood cells in whole
blood in suspension. It makes up about 55%
of total blood volume. It consists of about
92% water, with dissolved proteins like
albumins, globules and fibrinogen, glucose,
electrolytes, hormones and carbon(iv)oxide.
It is very important for the transporting
function of the blood.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option C
Sweat glands are highly vascular coiled and
simple fibular glands. They separate the
wastes from the blood and send it out in
the form of sweat. Sweat is formed of water
(99%), sodium chloride, lactic acid, some
urea and carbon(iv) oxide. Sebaceous
glands secrets sebum for the lubrication of
the skin. The outermost layer of the
epidermis consisting of dead cells that
slough off is the cornified or horny layer
and not gland, and the malpighian layer is
the innermost layer of the epidermis
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option D
Birds excrete nitrogenous wastes as uric
acid in form of a paste, a way to conserve
water.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option B
The skeleton supports the body, given it
shape and protect delicate organs in the
body . muscles are soft tissues found in
most animals, they function to produce
force and motion. A joint is the place where
two or more bones meet or articulate,
while a ligament joins two bones together.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A
Chitin(C8H1305N) is a nitrogenous poly
saccharide found in the exo skeleton of
arthropods. It is strengthened by calcium
compounds .
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option A
Pollination is the transfer of pollen grain
from a matured anther to a receptive
stigma. There are two types of pollinations.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Self pollination </explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Cross pollination
Self pollination is the transfer of pollen
grain from a matured anther of a flower to
the stigma of the same flower or that of
another flower on the same plant. Cross
pollination is the transfer of pollen grains
from a matured anther of a flower to the
stigma of flower of another plant of the
same or closely related specie. Fertilization
is the fusion of two haploid(n) gametes i.e.
male and female gametes to form a zygote.
Propagation is the process of creating new
plants from a variety of sources such as:
seed, cuttings, bulbs etc. Placentation is the
arrangement of ovules in the ovary.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option D
Petals and Sepals are non-essential whorls
of a flower. The sepals are the oustermost
whorl while the petals are next. The
essentials whorls are the androecium ( a
group of stamens or the male reproductive
organ) and the Gynoecium ( a group of
carpels or female reproductive organ)
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option A
The pituitary gland also called the master
gland is a protrusion off the bottom of the
hypothalamus at the base of the brain
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option A
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option A
There are two sensory cells in the eye. The
rods and the cones. Rods function mainly in
dim light and provide black and white vision
while cones are responsible for colour
vision as well eye colour sensitivity, they
function best in relatively bright light.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D
Anti-diuretic hormone or arginine
vasopressin helps to conserve body water
by reducing the loss of water in urine. A
diuretic agent is an agent that increases the
rate of urine formation, in the absence of
anti –diuretic hormones, the collecting
ducts are virtually impermeable to water
and it flows out as urine.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option C
Oestrogen is a reproductive hormone. It
causes the development of secondary
female sexual characteristics like
enlargement of breasts, widening of hips
etc. it is being produced by the ovaries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Cataracts are cloudy areas in the normally
clear lens inside the eye. There are two
47
types of cataracts: </explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Age –related cataracts
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Congenital or childhood cataracts.
Glycoma is a complicated disease in which
damage to the optic nerve leads progressive
irreversible vision loss. Astigmatism is an
optical defect in which vision is blurred due
to the inability of the optics of the eye to
focus a point object into a sharp focused
image in the retina. This may be due to an
irregular or toric curvature of the cornea or
lens. Presbyopia is a condition where with
age, the eye exhibits a progressive
diminished ability to focus on near objects.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option B
Only sewage is biodegradable. Cellophane,
crude oil and heavy metals are not
biodegradable.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option C.
Sleeping sickness is caused by trypanosome
– a protozoan. Malaria is caused by
plasmodium – a protozoan. River blindness
is caused by a filarial worm – Onchocerca
volvulus and yellow fever is caused by a
virus carried by aedes mosquito.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option B.
Biosphere is a part of the earth’s crust
where life can be found. It includes
atmosphere, the enveloping layer of air –
hydrosphere, the part of the biosphere
containing water and lithosphere, the solid
part of the biosphere.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option B.
Group AB people are universal recipients
while Group O people are universal donors.
Group A people can only take blood from A
or O Group and Group B people can only
take blood from B or O Group.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option C.
The clumping of red blood cells in the
presence of antibody is called agglutination.
It occurs when people are given blood
transfusion of the wrong blood group.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option B.
Plants that grow in arid places (dry
environments) are called xerophytes. The
morphological and anatomical
characteristic of xerophytes is called
xerophorphism. During hot dry weather or
in desert climates, animals aestivate.
Aestivation protects them from high
temperature or drought. Aestivation is a
state of animal dormancy characterized by
inactivity and a lower metabolic rate that is
entered in response to high temperature
and arid conditions.
</explanation></answer></answers>