<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation> Gen. 1 : 26
[26] Then God said, "Let us make man in our
image, after our likeness; and let them
have dominion over the fish of the sea, and
over the birds of the air, and over the cattle,
and over all the earth, and over every
creeping thing that creeps
upon the earth."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option C
The central theme of God’s covenant with
Israel was simply obedience. God required
of them the simple act of obedience; that is,
to keep His precepts and ordinances and by
so doing they will remain head over their
enemies and get blessed more abundantly.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation> Exod. 3 : 10 - 11
Proper study of the above scripture shows
that Moses’ statement was meant to
convince God that he was not competent
enough to face Pharoah and to face the
people of Israel. No wonder he asked God
what he will tell the children of Israel if they
ask him who sent him.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation> Judges 16 : 23 – 24
[23] Now the lords of the Philistines
gathered to offer a great sacrifice to Dagon
their god, and to rejoice; for they said, "Our
god has given Samson our enemy into our
hand."
[24] And when the people saw him, they
praised their god; for they said, "Our
god has given our enemy into our hand, the
ravager of our country, who has slain
many of us."
From the above scripture, it can be
understood that Samson was a terror to the
Philistines and he used his strength to
suppress them. The scripture further said
that Samson, at his death killed more
Philistines than he did while he lived.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation> Exod. 13 : 21 - 22
[21] And the LORD went before them by day
in a pillar of cloud to lead them
along the way, and by night in a pillar of fire
to give them light, that they might travel by
day and by night;
[22] the pillar of cloud by day and the pillar
of fire by night did not depart from before
the people.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option A
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation> 1 Kings. 15 : 11 – 12
[11] And Asa did what was right in the eyes
of the LORD, as David his father had done.
[12] He put away the male cult prostitutes
out of the land, and removed all the
idols that his fathers had made.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation> Exod. 1 : 20 - 21
[20] So God dealt well with the midwives;
and the people multiplied and grew
very strong.
[21] And because the midwives feared God
he gave them families.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation> 1 Sam. 15 : 22
[22] And Samuel said, "Has the LORD as
great delight in burnt offerings and
sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the
LORD? Behold, to obey is better than
sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of
rams.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation> 2 Sam. 12
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation> 1 Kings 3 : 16 - 27
[24] And the king said, "Bring me a sword."
So a sword was brought before the king.
[25] And the king said, "Divide the living
child in two, and give half to the one, and
half to the other."
[26] Then the woman whose son was alive
said to the king, because her heart
yearned for her son, "Oh, my lord, give her
the living child, and by no means
slay it." But the other said, "It shall be
neither mine nor yours; divide it."
[27] Then the king answered and said, "Give
the living child to the first woman,
and by no means slay it; she is its mother."
[28] And all Israel heard of the judgment
which the king had rendered; and they
stood in awe of the king, because they
perceived that the wisdom of God was in
him, to render justice.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation> 1 Kings 11 : 27 - 40
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation> 1 Kings 18 : 3 - 4
[3] And Ahab called Obadi'ah, who was over
the household. (Now Obadi'ah revered the
LORD greatly;
[4] and when Jez'ebel cut off the prophets of
the LORD, Obadi'ah took a hundred
prophets and hid them by fifties in a cave,
and fed them with bread and water.)
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation> 2 Kings 23 : 23 - 26
[23] but in the eighteenth year of King
Josi'ah this passover was kept to the LORD
in Jerusalem.
[24] Moreover Josi'ah put away the
mediums and the wizards and the teraphim
and the idols and all the abominations that
were seen in the land of Judah and in
Jerusalem, that he might establish the
words of the law which were written in the
book that Hilki'ah the priest found in the
house of the LORD.
[25] Before him there was no king like him,
who turned to the LORD with all his heart
and with all his soul and with all his might,
according to all the law of Moses; nor did
any like him arise after him.
[26] Still the LORD did not turn from the
fierceness of his great wrath, by which his
anger was kindled against Judah, because
of all the provocations with which
Manas'seh had provoked him.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation> Neh. 1 : 2 - 9
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation> Ezra 7 : 10
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation> Daniel 6 : 3
[3] Then this Daniel became distinguished
above all the other presidents and satraps,
because an excellent spirit was in him; and
the king planned to set him over the whole
kingdom.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option B
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation> Ezekiel 3 : 7
[7] But the house of Israel will not listen to
you; for they are not willing to listen to me;
because all the house of Israel are of a hard
forehead and of a stubborn heart.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation> Isaiah 6 : 8 - 13
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation> Luke 5 : 1 - 11
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation> John 2 : 7 – 11
[7] Jesus said to them, "Fill the jars with
water." And they filled them up to
the brim.
[8] He said to them, "Now draw some out,
and take it to the steward of the feast." So
they took it.
[9] When the steward of the feast tasted the
water now become wine, and did not
know where it came from (though the
servants who had drawn the water knew),
the steward of the feast called the
bridegroom
[10] and said to him, "Every man serves the
good wine first; and when men have
drunk freely, then the poor wine; but you
have kept the good wine until now."
[11] This, the first of his signs, Jesus did at
Cana in Galilee, and manifested his glory;
and his disciples believed in him.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation> Mark 5 : 1–17; Luke 8 : 26–37
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation> Luke 15 : 4 – 7
[4] "What man of you, having a hundred
sheep, if he has lost one of them, does
not leave the ninety-nine in the wilderness,
and go after the one which is lost,
until he finds it?
[5] And when he has found it, he lays it on
his shoulders, rejoicing.
[6] And when he comes home, he calls
together his friends and his neighbors,
saying to them, `Rejoice with me, for I have
found my sheep which was lost.'
[7] Just so, I tell you, there will be more joy
in heaven over one sinner who
repents than over ninety-nine righteous
persons who need no repentance.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation> Luke 10 : 17 - 20
[17] The seventy returned with joy, saying,
"Lord, even the demons are subject to us
in your name!"
[18] And he said to them, "I saw Satan fall
like lightning from heaven.
[19] Behold, I have given you authority to
tread upon serpents and scorpions, and over
all the power of the enemy; and nothing
shall hurt you.
[20] Nevertheless do not rejoice in this, that
the spirits are subject to you;
but rejoice that your names are written in
heaven."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation> Mark 9 : 2 – 9
[2] And after six days Jesus took with him
Peter and James and John, and led them up
a high mountain apart by themselves; and
he was transfigured before them,
[3] and his garments became glistening,
intensely white, as no fuller on earth
could bleach them.
[4] And there appeared to them Eli'jah with
Moses; and they were talking to Jesus.
[5] And Peter said to Jesus, "Master, it is
well that we are here; let us make
three booths, one for you and one for Moses
and one for Eli'jah."
[6] For he did not know what to say, for they
were exceedingly afraid.
[7] And a cloud overshadowed them, and a
voice came out of the cloud, "This is
my beloved Son; listen to him."
[8] And suddenly looking around they no
longer saw any one with them but Jesus
only.
[9] And as they were coming down the
mountain, he charged them to tell no one
what they had seen, until the Son of man
should have risen from the dead.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation> Luke 19 : 37 – 38
[37] As he was now drawing near, at the
descent of the Mount of Olives, the whole
multitude of the disciples began to rejoice
and praise God with a loud voice for all the
mighty works that they had seen,
[38] saying, "Blessed is the King who comes
in the name of the Lord! Peace in heaven
and glory in the highest!"
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option D
Mark 16 : 6 - 7
[6] And he said to them, "Do not be amazed;
you seek Jesus of Nazareth, who was
crucified. He has risen, he is not here; see
the place where they laid him.
[7] But go, tell his disciples and Peter that he
is going before you to Galilee; there you will
see him, as he told you."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation> John 15 : 1
[1] "I am the true vine, and my Father is the
vinedresser.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation> Acts 5 : 1 - 11
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation> Galatians 1 : 11 - 12
[11] For I would have you know, brethren,
that the gospel which was preached by me
is not man's gospel.
[12] For I did not receive it from man, nor
was I taught it, but it came through
a revelation of Jesus Christ.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation> Acts 13 : 7 – 11
[7] He was with the proconsul, Sergius
Paulus, a man of intelligence, who
summoned Barnabas and Saul and sought
to hear the word of God.
[8] But El'ymas the magician (for that is the
meaning of his name) withstood
them, seeking to turn away the proconsul
from the faith.
[9] But Saul, who is also called Paul, filled
with the Holy Spirit, looked intently at him
[10] and said, "You son of the devil, you
enemy of all righteousness, full of
all deceit and villainy, will you not stop
making crooked the straight paths of
the Lord?
[11] And now, behold, the hand of the Lord
is upon you, and you shall be blind
and unable to see the sun for a time."
Immediately mist and darkness fell upon
him and he went about seeking people to
lead him by the hand.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation> Acts 15 : 1 - 20
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation> Galatians 3 : 19
[19] Why then the law? It was added
because of transgressions, till the offspring
should come to whom the promise had been
made; and it was ordained by angels
through an intermediary.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation> 1 Pet. 5 : 5 – 7
[5] Likewise you that are younger be subject
to the elders. Clothe yourselves, all of you,
with humility toward one another, for "God
opposes the proud, but gives grace to the
humble."
[6] Humble yourselves therefore under the
mighty hand of God, that in due time he
may exalt you.
[7] Cast all your anxieties on him, for he
cares about you.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation> 2 Cor. 2 : 5 - 8
[5] But if anyone has caused pain, he has
caused it not to me, but in some measure
--not to put it too severely -- to you all.
[6] For such a one this punishment by the
majority is enough;
[7] so you should rather turn to forgive and
comfort him, or he may be overwhelmed by
excessive sorrow.
[8] So I beg you to reaffirm your love for
him.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation> 1 Cor. 12 : 4
[4] Now there are varieties of gifts, but the
same Spirit;…
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation> 2 Cor. 9 : 11
[11] You will be enriched in every way for
great generosity, which through us
will produce thanksgiving to God;…
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation> 2 Thess. 3 : 11 – 12
[11] For we hear that some of you are living
in idleness, mere busybodies, not doing any
work.
[12] Now such persons we command and
exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ to do their
work in quietness and to earn their own
living.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option B
Reference : 1 Thess. 4 : 15 - 16
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation> James 1 : 2 – 3
[2] Count it all joy, my brethren, when you
meet various trials,
[3] for you know that the testing of your
faith produces steadfastness.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation> 1 Pet. 2 : 18
[18] Servants, be submissive to your masters
with all respect, not only to the kind and
gentle but also to the overbearing.</explanation></answer></answers>