<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation> Matthew 14 : 26 – 27
[26] But when the disciples saw him walking
on the sea, they were terrified, saying, "It is
a ghost!" And they cried out for fear.
[27] But immediately he spoke to them,
saying, "Take heart, it is I; have no fear."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation> Luke 10 : 17
[17] The seventy returned with joy, saying,
"Lord, even the demons are subject to us
in your name!"
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation> Mark 11 : 10 – 11
[10] Blessed is the kingdom of our father
David that is coming! Hosanna in the
highest!"
[11] And he entered Jerusalem, and went
into the temple; and when he had looked
round at everything, as it was already late,
he went out to Bethany with the twelve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation> John 5 : 17 – 18
[17] But Jesus answered them, "My Father is
working still, and I am working."
[18] This was why the Jews sought all the
more to kill him, because he not only
broke the sabbath but also called God his
Father, making himself equal with God.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation> Matthew 16 : 16 – 20
[16] Simon Peter replied, "You are the
Christ, the Son of the living God."
[17] And Jesus answered him, "Blessed are
you, Simon Bar-Jona! For flesh and
blood has not revealed this to you, but my
Father who is in heaven.
[18] And I tell you, you are Peter, and on this
rock I will build my church, and the powers
of death shall not prevail against it.
[19] I will give you the keys of the kingdom
of heaven, and whatever you bind on
earth shall be bound in heaven, and
whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed
in heaven."
[20] Then he strictly charged the disciples to
tell no one that he was the Christ.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation> Luke 15 : 8 - 10
[8] "Or what woman, having ten silver coins,
if she loses one coin, does not
light a lamp and sweep the house and seek
diligently until she finds it?
[9] And when she has found it, she calls
together her friends and neighbors,
saying, `Rejoice with me, for I have found
the coin which I had lost.'
[10] Just so, I tell you, there is joy before the
angels of God over one sinner
who repents."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation> Luke 1 : 17
[17] and he will go before him in the spirit
and power of Eli'jah, to turn the hearts of
the fathers to the children, and the
disobedient to the wisdom of the just,
to make ready for the Lord a people
prepared."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation> Genesis 2 : 18 - 19
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation> Exodus 16 : 4
[4] Then the LORD said to Moses, "Behold, I
will rain bread from heaven for you; and the
people shall go out and gather a day's
portion every day, that I may prove them,
whether they will walk in my law or not.
The LORD gave the condition of gathering a
day’s portion every day is to test how
obedient the children of Israel were. This is
indicated in the last part of the verse
‘…whether they will walk in my law or not.’
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation> 11 : 12 - 13
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option A
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation> 1 Samuel 17 : 25
[25] And the men of Israel said, "Have you
seen this man who has come up? Surely he
has come up to defy Israel; and the man
who kills him, the king will enrich
with great riches, and will give him his
daughter, and make his father's house
free in Israel."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation> 1 Samuel 3 : 18
[18] So Samuel told him everything and hid
nothing from him. And he said, "It is
the LORD; let him do what seems good to
him."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation> 1 Kings 9 : 15
[15] And this is the account of the forced
labor which King Solomon levied to build
the house of the LORD and his own house
and the Millo and the wall of Jerusalem
and Hazor and Megid'do and Gezer
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation> Exodus 13 : 17
[17] When Pharaoh let the people go, God
did not lead them by way of the land of the
Philistines, although that was near; for God
said, "Lest the people repent when
they see war, and return to Egypt."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation> Gen. 37 : 26 - 27
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation> 1 Samuel 30 : 8
[8] And David inquired of the LORD, "Shall I
pursue after this band? Shall I
overtake them?" He answered him, "Pursue;
for you shall surely overtake and
shall surely rescue."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option B
This is indicated by the example given by
Paul concerning Jesus who humbled Himself
to the extent of dying on the cross. –
Philippians 2 : 6 - 8
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation> Romans 5 : 18
[18] Then as one man's trespass led to
condemnation for all men, so one man's act
of righteousness leads to acquittal and life
for all men.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation> 1 Peter 2 : 18
[18] Servants, be submissive to your masters
with all respect, not only to the kind and
gentle but also to the overbearing.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation> Romans 6 : 3
[3] Do you not know that all of us who have
been baptized into Christ Jesus were
baptized into his death?
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation> James 1 : 4
[4] And let steadfastness have its full effect,
that you may be perfect and complete,
lacking in nothing.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation> Romans 5 : 20
[20] Law came in, to increase the trespass;
but where sin increased, grace abounded all
the more, …
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation> Romans 13 : 14
[14] But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and
make no provision for the flesh, to gratify its
desires.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option B
In the last five verses of the 16th chapter of
1 Kings, the Bible describes the actions of
Ahab as being evil in the eyes of the Lord as
he erected an altar for Baal. This was the
reason why God commanded Elijah to
declare drought on the entire people of
Israel
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation> 1 Kings 21 : 19
[19] And you shall say to him, `Thus says the
LORD, "Have you killed, and also
taken possession?"' And you shall say to
him, `Thus says the LORD: "In the place
where dogs licked up the blood of Naboth
shall dogs lick your own blood."'"
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation> 2 Kings 24 : 2 – 4
[2] And the LORD sent against him bands of
the Chalde'ans, and bands of the Syrians,
and bands of the Moabites, and bands of
the Ammonites, and sent them against
Judah to destroy it, according to the word of
the LORD which he spoke by his servants the
prophets.
[3] Surely this came upon Judah at the
command of the LORD, to remove them out
of his sight, for the sins of Manas'seh,
according to all that he had done,
[4] and also for the innocent blood that he
had shed; for he filled Jerusalem with
innocent blood, and the LORD would not
pardon.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation> Hosea 14 : 2
[2] Take with you words and return to the
LORD; say to him, "Take away all iniquity;
accept that which is good
and we will render the fruit of our lips.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation> Jeremiah 4 : 2
[1] "If you return, O Israel, says the LORD, to
me you should return.
If you remove your abominations from my
presence, and do not waver,
[2] and if you swear, `As the LORD lives,'
in truth, in justice, and in uprightness,
then nations shall bless themselves in him,
and in him shall they glory."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation> 2 Kings 22 : 13
[13] "Go, inquire of the LORD for me, and
for the people, and for all Judah, concerning
the words of this book that has been found;
for great is the wrath of the LORD that is
kindled against us, because our fathers have
not obeyed the words of this book, to do
according to all that is written concerning
us."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation> Amos 6 : 12 – 14
[12] Do horses run upon rocks?
Does one plow the sea with oxen?
But you have turned justice into poison
and the fruit of righteousness into
wormwood -
[13] you who rejoice in Lo-debar,
who say, "Have we not by our own strength
taken Karnaim for ourselves?"
[14] "For behold, I will raise up against you
a nation, O house of Israel," says the LORD,
the God of hosts; "and they shall oppress
you from the entrance of Hamath to the
Brook of the Arabah."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation> 1 Samuel 5 : 4
[4] But when they rose early on the next
morning, behold, Dagon had fallen face
downward on the ground before the ark of
the LORD, and the head of Dagon and
both his hands were lying cut off upon the
threshold; only the trunk of Dagon
was left to him.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation> 2 Kings 23 : 15
[15] Moreover the altar at Bethel, the high
place erected by Jerobo'am the son of
Nebat, who made Israel to sin, that altar
with the high place he pulled down and he
broke in pieces its stones, crushing them to
dust; also he burned the Ashe'rah.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation> Jonah 1 : 2
[2] "Arise, go to Nin'eveh, that great city,
and cry against it; for their wickedness has
come up before me."
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation> John 9 : 1 – 6
[1] As he passed by, he saw a man blind
from his birth.
[2] And his disciples asked him, "Rabbi, who
sinned, this man or his parents,
that he was born blind?"
[3] Jesus answered, "It was not that this
man sinned, or his parents, but that
the works of God might be made manifest in
him.
[4] We must work the works of him who
sent me, while it is day; night comes,
when no one can work.
[5] As long as I am in the world, I am the
light of the world."
[6] As he said this, he spat on the ground
and made clay of the spittle and
anointed the man's eyes with the clay,
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option C
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation> John 3 : 19
[19] And this is the judgment, that the light
has come into the world, and men loved
darkness rather than light, because their
deeds were evil.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation> Acts 5 : 1 - 11
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation> John 20 : 2 – 3
[2] So she ran, and went to Simon Peter and
the other disciple, the one whom
Jesus loved, and said to them, "They have
taken the Lord out of the tomb, and we
do not know where they have laid him."
[3] Peter then came out with the other
disciple, and they went toward the tomb.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation> Acts 13 : 4
[2] So she ran, and went to Simon Peter and
the other disciple, the one whom
Jesus loved, and said to them, "They have
taken the Lord out of the tomb, and we
do not know where they have laid him."
[3] Peter then came out with the other
disciple, and they went toward the tomb.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation> Luke 24 : 18 – 23
[18] Then one of them, named Cle'opas,
answered him, "Are you the only visitor
to Jerusalem who does not know the things
that have happened there in these
days?" [19] And he said to them, "What
things?" And they said to him, "Concerning
Jesus of Nazareth, who was a prophet
mighty in deed and word before God and all
the
people, [20] and how our chief priests and
rulers delivered him up to be condemned to
death, and crucified him. [21] But we had
hoped that he was the one to redeem Israel.
Yes, and besides all this, it is now the third
day since this happened. [22] Moreover,
some women of our company amazed us.
They were at the tomb early in the morning
[23] and did not find his body; and they
came back saying that they had even seen a
vision of angels, who said that he was alive.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation> Acts: 2
Peter, while addressing the people on the
day of Pentecost, made the statement in
verse 32 of Acts. 2 concerning the
resurrection of Jesus.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation> John 3 : 18
[18] He who believes in him is not
condemned; he who does not believe is
condemned already, because he has not
believed in the name of the only Son of
God.</explanation></answer></answers>