<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Two positively related variables can be depicted graphically on
curve sloping upwardly from left to right to illustrate a type of direct relationship that exist
between the two variables. A good and familiar example of this is a “supply curve”.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: For an inferior good more of it is demanded at lower income.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option C.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A normalize statement of economics pays attention to “what ought
to be” in the sense of making ethical judgments as to the desirability of different policies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Utility is defined as the satisfaction derived from the consumption
of a particular good or service.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The value of elasticity of demand lies between zero and one. The
price elasticity of demanded calculated equals 0.83 which implies fairly inelastic.
When the price rises from N5.00 to N8.00 and the quantity demanded falls from 200 units to
190 units, it implies that: A 60% rise in price causes a 5% fall in quantity demanded. It indicates
that the rise in price causes less than proportionate change in quantity demanded, meaning that
the demand for the commodity is fairly inelastic.
29
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A planned economy is otherwise known as socialism. An economy
that is owned and controls by government, every activity of such an economy is being maintain
and control by government and its sole aim is social welfare and development.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B.
12
1
6x
2
6y
12
Py
MUx
Px
MUy
+ =
+ =
3y + 6x = 12
In the calculation above, the consumer has N12.00 to spend, the combination of the two
commodities he should consume in order to maximize his utility will be to consume 3 units of y
and 6 units of x, as y and x cost N2.00 and N1.00 respectively.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: An increase in the demand of a commodity occurs when there is
change in other factors affecting demand other than price. An increase in demand is a rightward
shift in demand curve given a fixed supply curve will lead to rise in price.
Rise in both price and quantity of the commodity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: A capital intensive method of production will be adopted if the ratio
of labour to resources availability is small.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option B.
At output 60 units, the total cost (TC) is N150.00 and the fixed cost (FC) is N60.00, this implies
that the variable cost (VC) is N90.00. Therefore, the Average Variable Cost (AVC) is Total Output
(TO) divided by Variable cost (VC). Thus represented:
TO = 60
TC = N150.00
FC = N60.00
VC = N90.00
∴ AVC = N1.5
N60
N90 =
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option B.
At output 30 units, the Average Total Cost (ATC) is
30
N120
Output
TC = = N4.00
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option B.
A monopolist as a price maker has greater influence and control over the price and output. And
this is in a bid to maximize profit. His demand curve is sharply downward sloping.
30
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A positive relationship exists between supply of a commodity and its
price due to the fact that producer and manufacture supplies more as price goes up and this is
also known as revenue maximization.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: In the short run, firm can only vary variable inputs only.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Price elasticity of supply measures the responsiveness of supply to
change in price since price is a determinant of quantity supplied.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The long run period is a period in which all inputs are varied and a
period long enough to accommodate a bigger size of plant through planning.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A market is imperfect when it lacks at least one of the characteristics
of a perfect market. A market that has many buyers and few sellers likely to be subject to
control by few sellers through price manipulation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Near-Money is any asset that can be readily converted to cash
either real or financial asset.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Acceptance of deposit is a unique function of commercial bank.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Money market provides debt instruments in short-term while capital
market provides debt instrument in long-term.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Value added is the contribution to total production made by a firm
in the production process. In this case, it is calculated by subtracting from its sales its purchases
from other firms.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The non-bank financial institutions are those that do not accept
deposits from customers like that of commercial banks and this is where insurance companies
and other belongs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Inflation originating from excess demand that was caused by
increase in money supply. The fullest form of demand-pull inflation is when excess demand
occurs in both factor and product markets.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Among every other instrument used by the central bank in
monetary control, discount rate is the strongest; it determines other rates. The higher the rate
of discount the more discouraged is commercial banks to borrow.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A listed securities are the ones traded in the floor of stock exchange
market.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The difference between the rate of inflation between 1999 and year
2000 equals 144.05% minus 140.03%.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The principle justifies nations to specialize in those economic
activities that can be performed relatively better and at lowest cost.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option C: Explanation: The decisions are made by the sole proprietor alone so there is no
room for conflict.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Distinguishing capital expenditure from recurrent expenditure has
to do with the nature of good or service involved. If the good or service to be provided is once in
a while and fixed, then, it is categorized under capital expenditure; but if good or service
involved requires continual or frequent financial attention, then, it is a re-current expenditure.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Demand and supply forces determines exchange rate under floating
exchange rate exchange rate regime other than fixed exchange rate regime.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Revenue allocation in a country has to be shared between the
different tiers of government in order to ensure financial viability of the country.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Lower income earners are not adequately enjoying advantages of
trade discount since they seldom buy in large quantity or in bulk.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Public enterprises are being privatized due to their inability to meet
up with the expected goals and objectives of creating them -- Operational inefficiency.
31
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation; The effectiveness of devaluation of domestic currency depends on
relative elasticity of demand for domestic goods by foreign buyers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: They are corporate entities that has a legal identity separate from
that of its owners; they are an incorporated companies that stand legally on its own right, they
can be sued or sue.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Disposable income is defined as income less tax. Increase in the
personal income tax will lower disposable income.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: IBRD is a typical example of development banking institution.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Standard of living can be measured using the average income of a
country; it is obtained by dividing a country’s total income by its population. The real national
per capital income would have taken care of inflation rate.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Expatriates and multi-national companies are needed in the
refineries because it involves high skills and huge capitals to function the mechanism effectively.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The definition of an industry emphasizes on companies
concentrated on similar products and consuming closely similar inputs or raw materials.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Labour is being demanded for in order to commence the production
of goods and services.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option B.
Craft unionism refers to an approach to union organizing that seeks to unify workers in a
particular craft or trade they work in i.e. organization of workers of similar skills.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Oil spillage will pollute water and make fishing and farming
unpracticable.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Defined as a worker’s movement between one type of job and
another. The amount of mobility depends greatly on the fineness of the occupational
classification chosen.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: When the available resources are not enough or inadequate relative
to the population size.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option C.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Price of agricultural produce cannot be fixed due to uncertainty in
volume and quality of farm produce.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: All the persons of a country who are employed for a minimum
number of hours per week, e.g. twelve, or are self-employed or are unemployed. The most
difficult problems of labour force measurement arise from counting the unemployed and those
engaged in economic activity within households.</explanation></answer></answers>