<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Balance of payments is credit and debit in international transaction. It is
the record of the transactions between the residents of one country and the rest of the world in a
given time period.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option A.
One of the causes of the present high rate of inflation in Nigeria is increasing factor cost.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option D. Ensuring an efficient usage of the available resources that cut across a nation leads to
a rapid development and optimum production since ‘efficient’ means getting maximum from a given
input.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Quota, by definition, is a restricted supply of a good or service. When
the importation of a commodity is limited to a definite quantity, the trade control means used is
known as quotas or quantitative restrictions. Import quotas are used to protect domestic industries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Inflationary gap, excess of aggregate demand over aggregate supply.
This gap is the cause of demand pull inflation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Private limited company is founded by two to fifty persons who buy
shares in the company.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Fiscal policy is the taxation and expenditure policy of a government. The
extent to which fiscal policy can be employed depends on what a government can observe of
economic behavior.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Ad valorem tax is an indirect levied as a percentage of the value of a
transaction. Sales tax, excise duties and value added taxes are major examples. In calculating such
taxes, either the final price of the good or service or the value added at a particular stage of
production is the basis. This tax reduces the amount of revenue that a firm obtains from the sales of
a good or a service.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Absolute advantage is an early theory of international trade which state
that one country enters into trade with another because it has greater productivity than that
country in a particular industry or industries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Mixed economy is an economy combining the methods and goals of
capitalism and socialism, particularly by encouraging the growth of the public sector.
39
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Standard deviation measures the dispersion of values of a variable
about its arithmetic mean that is calculated as the square root of the sum of the differences
between each of those values and the arithmetic mean divided by the number of values minus one.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: From the curves, a rational consumer will choose to consume at J, where
the price is lowest.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A change in demand for a normal good means that the demand changes
as price changes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: As in the chain of distribution; from the producer – wholesaler – retailerfinal
consumer. The production process is yet to be completed if the goods produced have not
reached the final consumer.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Reason been that ordinal utility subject satisfaction expressed as
ordered preferences. This makes possible the ranking of satisfactions as first, second, third and so
forth without having to state the amount by which one satisfaction is greater or less than another.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Median is the middle value (or arithmetic mean of the two middle
values when there is an even number of values) of numbers arranged in order of magnitude.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The opportunity cost of moving from K to L means that 2 units of rice
have been forgone in order to purchase 5 units of beans.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Black market is an unauthorized market transactions contrary to
governmental regulations. When prices are set by government below the equilibrium, a black
market will occur. Markets of this kind are often found when there are price or exchange controls or
the restriction of trading to a list of authorized dealers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation:
C = N160 + N(36 x 20) = N160 + N720 = N880
∴ AC = N44.00
20
N880 =
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A movement from M to T implies that there has been increases in price
since a positive relationship exist between supply and price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The change from T to N implies that the supply curve had shifted from
its initial position to a new position. This symbolizes increase in supply.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The new equilibrium point, according to the demand and supply curves
is E2, because this is the point where the new demand curve, D2D2, intersects the new supply curve,
S2S2.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>option B.
A firm operating at full capacity will experience rising short-run total costs when prices of its variable
inputs rise.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation; The cost of cotton used is categorized under the variable cost because
cotton quantity goes with the level of output.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The two goods involved are jointly supplied.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Census conduction by a nation enables her to formulate its plan –
policies and implementation procedure.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>option D. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option A.
40
The involvement of government in agricultural business in Nigeria is most manifested in the
procurement and distributions of fertilizers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option B.
The downstream activities of oil companies in Nigeria involve refining and distribution.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option A.
The labour force in Nigeria falls between the ages of 18 and 60. In the Public Service Rule, the
allowable age for an appointee is 18 years and above. After employment, the employee can serve
for a maximum of 35 years or cannot exceed 60 years in service.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Distribution chain is the routing of goods been produced by
manufacturers or producer to the final consumer. The standard, correct and more economical
distribution chain is: Producer> Wholesaler> Retailer> Consumer.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option A. A major cause of the slow pace of industrialization in Nigeria is inadequate skilled
labour or technical know-how.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Natural growth rate is the different between death rate and birth rate
since both death and birth are natural occurrence.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Advertising is a communication activity used to influence potential
buyers or others who can help the advertiser to reach defined goals. For firms, it is a selling cost
incurred with the hope of increasing sales.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Central Bank maintains a stable price system by preventing inflation,
deflation, etcetera through its monetary/fiscal policies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Total product curve is an inverse moving catalogue of marginal revenue
curve because marginal revenue is being realized through marginal cost. Thus, as total product curve
moves to the pick, marginal revenue equals zero (relative to a horizontal axis) any further
movement of total product curve make marginal revenue goes negative.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Central bank is a financial institution which ultimately guarantees the
liquidity of the banking system as a whole by setting interest rates for discounting and short-term
bills of banking system. A central bank is able to exert a powerful influence over the size of money
supply.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: An open economy is an economy that engaged in international trade
and the degree of openness can be measured by its imports or exports as a proportion of GDP.
In an open economy, the GNP is measured as C + I + G + X – M, where C is consumption, I is
investment, G is government spending, X is export and M is import.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A monopolistic competitive market is similar to PERFECT COMPETITION,
apart from the crucial assumption of PRODUCT DIFFERENTIATION which has the effect of
introducing the selling cost.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option C.
The primary function of non-bank financial institutions is to mobilize savings for investment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
Y = bY + I
Y = 0.8Y + I
I = Y – 0.8Y = 0.2Y
C = 0.8Y
41
∴ M = x change in investment
1 MPC
1
−
= 5
0.2
x 1 1
1 0.8
1 = =
−
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The profit maximizing output in the short-run of a monopolist, according
to the diagram is Q2.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: A market which issues securities to raise long-term capital.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: GDP is total output of goods and services produced within a country in a
particular time period.</explanation></answer></answers>