<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Supplier of a perishable product will continue to supply despite a fall
in price since product that is not supplied to the market may go bad as a result of lack of storage
facilities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Factors of production are being demanded for in order to make
production of goods and services effectively done.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
From the graph,
At Y, S = 18, T = 13
Y = change in ST = 5
19
At X, S = 3, T = 4
X = difference in ST = 1
Substitution of X for Y = 5 : 1.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Forgone alternative, the student let go ruler in order to have an
exercise book since the available resources (#30) on him cannot buy both ruler and exercise
book.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C. Shift in supply simply means a change in supply which is caused by other factors
affecting supply other than price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Inductive and Deductive methodologies are the two scientific mode
of reasoning in economics. Reasoning from particular to general and observing from general to
particular.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A central planned economy is a type of economy that is controls by
the government.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Complementary demand is a demand for goods that can be
consumed in conjunction with another.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Stock exchange belongs to secondary market and this type of
market deals in sales of an existing share unlike the primary market that issues new shares.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>option D. Explanation: One of the uses of national income is international comparison of
growth rate.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: When a bank carry out its activities in a location without having
branches elsewhere such bank is called a unit bank. Community bank/micro-finance bank.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option A.
Deflator = 100
N50
N65
100
base year
Current year × ⎟⎠
⎞
⎜⎝
× = ⎛ = N130.00
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation:
x Investment
1 MPC
M 1
−
=
2.5
0.4
x 1 1
1 0.6
1 = =
−
=
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Capital market is a market that engages in long term loan and
securities. Insurance company would prefer long term to short term investment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Liquidity preference is desire to hold money as an asset as against
investing it as shares or stock.
20
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Inflation its self is persistence increase in general price level.
Therefore, creeping inflation is a gentle or very slow but consistent increase in general price
level.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Nigeria Deposit Insurance Corporation (NDIC) is an agent of
monetary authority that insures commercial banks’ deposit whereby protecting the depositors
in case of bank failure.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Contractionary fiscal policy involves reduction in government
expenditure in increment in taxation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Wholesalers and retailers are in the middle in the chain of
distribution between producers and final consumers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Under population is defined as a situation whereby the available
resources are more than the total number of population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Like every other market determine price, equilibrium wage rate
determines by the forces of demand and supply for labor.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Malthus predicted economic doom arising from the relative growth
in population over the means of sustenance.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: When labour is more efficient the output per unit of a labour
employed increases.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: As output of a firm increases its average fixed cost tends to decrease
continuously but will not get to zero.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Below equilibrium price is excess demand, so at price #60 the excess
demand here is the different between equilibrium quantity and total quantity supplied which is
300 less 200.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option D.
The equilibrium level of monopoly is that level of output in which the marginal revenue equals
marginal cost.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: External economies are benefits that accrue to a firm as a result of
concentration or industrialization of industries in a particular area. They include: locally available
skilled labour, training, research and development facilities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option C/D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: This is an abolition of governmental regulations, especially for prices
and the operations of publicly owned organizations, with the aims of lowering prices through
more competition, and of stimulating the growth of small businesses.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation:
PRICE D1 S1
S0
D1
D0
QUANTITY
21
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Issuing of shares is the major external source of finance for limited
liability companies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Poverty, low level of literacy and low income are enough indicators
of underdevelopment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option C.
The NNPC was established on 1st April, 1977 as a result of a merger between the Nigerian
National Oil Corporation (NNOC) and the Ministry of Petroleum resources was to, among other
things, oversee all the activities involving refining and production of petroleum products so as to
satisfy domestic consumption of the products.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Devaluation of currency makes domestic goods cheaper in the
international market thereby promoting exportation that will reduce balance of payments.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Indirect tax—tax levied on commodities which are shifted to final
consumers by the production units.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: importation and exportation are the two forces that determine the
type of balance of payment of a country. If import is more that export a country is running on
deficit balance of payment and vice versa. Therefore, substitution of importation improves
balance of payment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option B. When an economy is experiencing depression, one of the measures to stimulate
recovery is by ejecting more money into an economy the money can be borrowed within or
outside the economy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Infrastructural facilities encompass all necessary and needed
instruments (skilled and unskilled) that can facilitate development of industry. Inadequacy of
these infrastructural facilities will hinder the growth of industry.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>option D. Explanation: Privatization increases production efficiency since it guide against
waste and ineffectiveness. A privately owned company works towards achieving goals and
objectives efficiently and to maximize values.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: African Development Bank Whose objective is to promote
infrastructural development among member states.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: As country gets more developed, it moves from primary stage of
production to secondary and tertiary stages of production thereby reduces the number of
labour force engaged in the primary production in which agriculture is inclusive.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option A.
Opportunity cost of a unit of cotton in terms of cocoa in Nigeria is that unit of both commodities
in Ghana:
5
20 = 4 units
Opportunity cost of a unit of cotton in term of cocoa in Ghana is that unit of both commodities
in Nigeria:
30
60 = 2 units ⇒ 4 units for Ghana, 2 for Nigeria.</explanation></answer></answers>