<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: it indicates fixed in the quantity supplied of a commodity
irrespective of the change in its price. This is the case of a perfectly inelastic supply curve which
means the responsiveness of quantity supplied to change in price is zero.
P
2 Supply curve
1
0
1 2 3 4 5 Q
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Change in supply is the increase or decrease in supply of gods and
services due to changes in the other factors affecting supply other than the price (e.g. cost of
production, weather, etc.)
8
Graphical Illustration
Price S2
S0
E
S1 S2
S1 S0
Quantity
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: inductive reasoning involves drawing a conclusion from particular to
general. By saying economists distill principles from facts, we are describing the inductive or
empirical method.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation : if M is at the point of reflection where total utility is at its maximum
then marginal utility will be equal to zero since as total utility increases up to the apex the
marginal utility decreases gradually to zero in which any further attempt to increase the TU will
lead MU to negative.
Graphical Illustration
U
TU
Q
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Because the demand curve slope downward from left to right,
meaning that less quantity will be demanded at higher price ceteris paribus.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Indifference curve is the locus of points-particular combination or
bundle of goods- which yield the same utility. While budget line showing the maximum amount
of goods in different combinations, which a consumer can obtain from his or her income. Given
the indifference map (all the indifference curves which rank the preferences of the consumer) of
the consumer and its budget line, the equilibrium is defined as the point of tangency of the
budget line with the highest possible indifference curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The price elasticity of demand of that particular good is inelastic
because 0.43 less than 1 and increase in price of such price inelastic demand good can only led to NET
GAIN.
9
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Scale of preference is the ordering of consumer’s want in order of
their priority. It is also a list that shows the need of a consumer in order of magnitude.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option: C. Explanation: There exist a positive relationship between price and quantity
supplied of a good which implies a change in quantity supplied resulting from change in price
other than other factors affecting supply.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Price control is a form of government intervention in economies
when economy is at disequilibrium. Because in the mixed economy system resources allocation
is done by private and public sector.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option C.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: A major problem facing economies is resources allocation in that
economic units tend to want more than the economy can provide. Scarcity simply means limited
in supply. If goods were in abundant supply, there wouldn’t have been the problem of scarcity;
the problem of scarcity necessitates a choice among alternative uses of scarce resources.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Ans : Option D. Explanation: Free enterprise market , the interaction of demand and supply
forces are just automatically operate to allocate resources into an alternative uses.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The adoption of scientific method in the study of human behavior in
economics allowed it to be regarded as social science.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: In the long run, there exist the needs for a very large scale output
that will require variation in all inputs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: This is a technical relationship between inputs and outputs of goods
and services.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: With perfect knowledge of market condition (price) no single buyer
or seller can be discriminated against since neither of the parties (buyer and seller) is price giver.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>option C. Explanation: When a firm enjoys location advantage and uses it to influence the
price it is no longer operating under perfect market because of its ability to influence the price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Average variable cost, when combined with price, indicates whether
or not a firm should shut down production in the short run. If price is greater than average
variable cost, then the firm is able to pay all variable cost and a portion of fixed cost. Even
though it might be incurring an economic loss, it will lose less by producing that by shutting
down production. If, however, price is less than average variable cost, then the firm is better off
shutting down production.
10
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: At equilibrium price, quantity demanded of a good equals quantity
supplied of that good.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: With division of labour, a worker doesn’t need to move from one
piece of work to another and having been specialized on a given task he now concentrate
actively without wasting time.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Fixed cost is a cost that does not change an increase or decrease in
the amount of goods or services produced. Rent on building does not have to change if the
output of the firm must increase or decrease.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Fixing price below equilibrium is called price ceiling. The price has
been fixed below market determined price and at lower price more quantity of goods are
demanded by consumers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option B/A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: An industry is defined as group of firms producing similar or
identical products.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: This is evident.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Equity financing is one of main sources of raising fund by joint stock
companies from member of the public through issuing of shares and giving the shareholders
certificate of participation in ownership of the corporation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Environmental pollution can occur when a large number of firm
concentrated in particular area emit different waste substances into the environment which are
capable of polluting the environment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: unlimited liability is one of the main disadvantages of sole
proprietorship because in the event of failure in the business, the assets of the business, his
private assets and other properties may be claimed by his creditor.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Extension service is one of the approaches used to promote
acquisition of new techniques of farming among farmers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The capital market is the market for medium-term or long term
loans.
11
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The normal channel of distribution is from producer to wholesaler
and to the retailer and to the final consumer.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Ans : Option A. Explanation: Discount rate is the rate at which commercial banks borrows from
central banks. When this rate increases commercial banks are discouraged from borrowing and
their ability to lend to the public will be reduced. Thereby implies tight monetary policy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Ans : Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: National debt can be internal or external when debt is incurred that
means expenditure is more than income which is known as deficit budget.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Money is the most liquid asset of all assets. But it may lose much of
its value in time of inflation. Therefore, money is not a perfect store of value because its
purchasing power can change.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Nigeria operates federal system of government which has three(3)
tiers and revenue sharing is based on these tiers which are; federal, state and local government.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A progressive tax is a tax system that takes a larger percentage of
income from people earning larger income (e.g) P.A.Y.E pay As You earn.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Economic growth implies increase in volume of output overtime and
it can be accelerated through the encouragement of savings and consumptions.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Workers tend to be more efficient when they are exposed to
regular training and education.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Wage is the reward for labour as factor input and which is also
called price of labour.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Net National Product is defined as Gross National Product less
Depreciation and depreciation is also called capital consumption allowance.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: A sustainable growth in population will allow balancing of
population growth (lower birth rate) and means of sustaining the growth.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Loans for infrastructural investments are investments that cover the
basic area of an economy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: No nation is self reliance or self sufficient, nations must trade with
each other since there is variability natural recourses endowment.
</explanation></answer></answers>