<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Production Possibility curve shows the maximum combination of
different commodities that can be produced with a given resources.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Deregulation is the removal of government control or imposed
constraint or conditions in the economy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Inductive reasoning is an economic methodology that involves
inference from a particular to general.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Modal score is the figure with the highest frequency or occurrence.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The law of demand states that the higher the price, the lower the
quantity demanded and vice-versa. However, sometimes, the demand of commodities is subject
to what is in vogue irrespective of the price i.e. people’s taste and fashion.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A change in supply implies the entire shift of supply curve either to
the right or to the left.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Ans; Option A. Explanation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>option C. Explanation: Cars and petrol are jointly demanded to satisfy a particular demand.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Marginal utility is the satisfaction derived from the consumption of
an additional unit of a commodity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The law of diminishing marginal utility states that the amount of
satisfaction derived from the consumption of successive units of the same commodity will
decline. The law is used to explain the downward-sloping nature of the normal demand curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Consumer surplus is the difference between how much a consumer
is willing to pay for a good and how much is eventually pays.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option D.
68
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>option B. Explanation: Equilibrium quantity is the point at which Qd=Qs
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: When price increases to #3, excess supply is calculated thus: Qs-Qd
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Technology to a very extent influence supply. It is the availability of
technology that will determine the method of production (i.e., either labour or capital intensive)
as well as the processing and storage facilities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Market composition indicates the types and nature of market which
ranges from one market to another. It is the composition of a market that will indicate whether
it is a perfect competitive market or an imperfect competitive market such as monopoly,
monopsony, oligopoly, duopoly etc.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: From the diagram. At price P, Qd = 20 and Qs= 40units. Hence, it can
be deduced that there is an excess supply of 20units (i.e Qs –Qd = 40 – 20= 20units)
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: In a agrarian sector, a bumper period is a time when there are
surplus farm produce or outputs such that its supply exceed demands. Whenever demand
exceed supply, the price of such a product ceteris paribus. However, the government can
sometimes interfere with the forces of demand and supply by setting a maximum price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: In production process, two methods are adopted i.e., it’s either
labour or capital intensive. Labour intensive method of production involves the use of more
people and less machine for production processes which subsequently increase the demand for
labour. Capital intensive method of production involves the use of less people and more
machine for production processes which subsequently decrease the demand for labor.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Marginal cost is the additional cost a firm incurs as a result of the
production of a unit more of a production. Therefore, 11 at 36 – 10 units at #</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>396 – 250 =
#146.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Marginal cost rises while Average cost decreases and vice-versa.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Entry and exit point for firm place restrictions on the number of
participants.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: A monopolist is a single seller of a commodity that has no close
substitute.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The output approach to measuring national income is based on the
computation of the value added on the input, for example, flour is turned to bread or cake as a
result of the value added to the flour.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: An injection in the circular flow of income is government spending
which can be through relief, sick benefit, free education, pensions etc.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Interest rate is the cost of borrowing or lending i.e., the cost of
parting with liquidity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Inflation occurs as a result of persistent rise in the general price level
which can occur as a result of excess demand or an increase in the cost of production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Ans : Option C.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Monetary policy is a deliberate action by which a government
controls and regulates inflation through the use of interest rate, open market operation etc.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Fiscal policy is a deliberate process by which government uses taxes
and government expenditure to control and regulate inflation.
69
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>option B. Explanation: Indirect tax is compulsory payment levied on goods services whose
burden can be shifted to the consumer.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Economic development is a multi-dimensional and structural growth
in the economy such that it improves the welfare and standard of living of people.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Economic growth is an increase in GDP or NI.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A major problem facing the agricultural sector is the problem of
inadequate infrastructural.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Farm inputs, to a very large extent, determine farm outputs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: A major determinant used in locating an industry is the nearness to
raw materials. Lime stone is an essential raw material in the production of cement.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Ans : Option C. Explanation: Export promotion strategy is the strategy directed towards
exporting of more goods.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Upstream activities in the oil and gas industry involve all the
exploration processes involved in the oil and gas industry. Downstream-activities involve all the
processing.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Privatization is a deliberate process or policy in which publiclyowned
companies are being controlled and managed by individuals or group of individuals.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Ans; Option B. Explanation: Capital market is a market where long-term loans are raised or
borrowed to finance business.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Labour force is the working population in an economy, also known
as active population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The shaded area represents an under-populated area or underpopulation.
Consequently, the population policy will be to encourage early marriage so as to
optimize the population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Death decreases population while birth increases it. In a situation
whereby death rate exceeds birth rate the logic conclusion will be that it leads to decreasing
population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: A policy of fixing minimum price implies that a commodity can be
sold above an equilibrium price but cannot be sold below it.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The use of different currencies is a major barrier in international
trade.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: No matter how irrational or stupid a producer or manufacturer may
seems, he will never sell a product below the cost price. Consequently, a higher rent or land will
lead to a higher cost of producing maize.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Ans; Option A. Explanation: Active population = #50 million,
Unemployed = #5million
Hence, unemployment rate = 5/50 * 100 equals 10%
</explanation></answer></answers>