<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B.
The price elasticity of the demand curve facing a monopoly firm determines if the marginal
revenue received by the monopoly is positive (elastic demand) or negative (inelastic demand).
This relationship is imperative for the profit-maximizing production decision that involves
equality between MR and MC. The implication of this relation implies that a monopoly can only
maximize profit in the elastic range of the demand curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: From the diagram, capital goods flow to business firms, labour
inputs also flow to business firms, the goods and services produced by the business firms flow to
households while the wages also flow to households.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The firm’s short-run profit-maximizing output is where MC = MR. At
output 450kg, the marginal cost equals marginal revenue.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option B.
The Securities and Exchange Commission is the sole regulatory authority of the capital market in
Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B.
Y = C + I
Y = 50 + 0.75Y + 45
48
Y – 0.75Y = 5
0.25Y = 5; ∴ Y = N20m
0.25
5 =
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: In a perfectively competitive market, price is determines by the
interaction of the two market forces(demand and supply)
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Discount house is a financial institution which borrows Monet at
Call from banks and other institutions and invests in Treasury bill.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Gross National Product (GNP), if measured using output approach, is
the monetary value of all the outputs of each sector of an economy within a given period of
time, usually one year.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The number of persons per unit of land area. Population density
varies greatly from country to country. Some less developed countries appear to have low
population densities because a large proportion of their land areas is uninhabitable mountains,
desert and swamps.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option D.
There must be an increase in agricultural product as long as the tax on inelasticity of supply is
borne by the consumer.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Petroleum industry generates revenues for the government through
the exportation of crude oil and gains from multi-national refinery companies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Negotiation-a bargaining power between two parties.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Localization of an industry is an act of siting industries in a place
where is ready market for their products.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: 12% represent Growth rate, 52% represent Death rate.
Growth rate= Birth rate – Death rate
12% = X – 52%
X=52% + 12%
X representing Birth rate which equals 64%
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option D
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B.
The central principle guiding long-run production is return to scale, which indicates how
production responds to proportional changes in all inputs.
49
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Yes, because at break even taking place where total cost is equal
total revenue( i.e average cost is equal to average revenue)
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Increase in the quantity supplied implies movement along a supply
curve which can only be influenced by change in price of the particular commodity involved.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option A. The long run is a production-planning period in which a firm varies all factors of
production to be in line with the level of demand. At this period, no factor is fixed. All factors
and costs are variable.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Division of labour is the specialization of productive activity either
by persons in different occupational groups undertaking particular tasks or by dividing a task
into its component operations.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option B. When the prevailing market price is greater than the equilibrium price, there
would be excess supply arising from the fall in demand. The producer or supplier would now
hoard in order to create artificial scarcity for the goods so as to equate the demand with the
supply.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Production function is defined as the relationship between input
and output.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Since marginal utility is an additional satisfaction derived from the
consumption of a commodity, a consumer is at equilibrium price where quantity ratios are
equal.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>.Option D. Explanation: A buyer haggles in order to beat down the price of a commodity so
as to maximize utility and get the highest possible value of money spent.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: implies oppositely affected variables.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The total Utility is at its peak.
Util
TU
MU
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Ans : Option A. Explanation: There is economic freedom in Free Enterprise Economy as
individual is free to invest in any business and every consumer has choice of commodity.
50
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The median in the distribution is the quantity that is found in the
middle when arranged in ascending or descending order, therefore, in the example above, the
median quantity is 4kg.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option B.
Price Qty PQ
40
48
55
60
70
6
5
4
3
2
240
240
220
180
140
20 1020
Mean equals sum of PQ divided by sum of Q
i.e., Mean = N1020 divided by 20
= N51
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Production process is complete when the goods and services produced
reach the final consumers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The price index shows an increase in the prices of goods and services
and when prices rise, it reduces the standard of living of the people; therefore, an increase in index
number from 100% or 128% means that the standard of living has fallen by 28%.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: plan implementation requires some strategies that are more of
managerial efficiency which Nigeria is lacking.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Equity financing an act of raising funds through the issues of shares to
the public.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Nigeria will produce 9000 units of groundnuts since she has to specialize
on the commodity in which her comparative advantage is greater and the resources being wasted
on cocoa will be used to produce additional 1000 units of groundnuts.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: If Nigeria now specializes on the production of the crop she can
efficiently produce and her total output rises from 8000 units of groundnuts and 1000 units of cocoa
to 16,000 units of groundnut only. She would have a difference of 7000 units of output as an
increase.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The World Bank gives long-term loan to developing countries to assist
them in financing their infrastructural projects.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Growth is a pre-requisite to development. Without economic growth
there is no economic development. Economic growth refers to change in the quantity of goods and
51
services produced in an economy while economic development refers to the structural
transformation in the standard of living from the primary sector to secondary sector.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option D.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Partnership and sole-proprietorship business organizations have the
feature of unlimited liability which implies that in the event of failure, the owners may forfeit their
personal property.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The persistent depreciation in the exchange rate of Naira makes the
value of Naira to fall and this makes the goods and services to be costlier.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option B. Increased government spending on public works would increase the level of
employment since more organizations and companies will be built.
50 Option C.
European Union is an international organization formed to regulate trade relations among member
states.</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option B. Increased government spending on public works would increase the level of
employment since more organizations and companies will be built.
50 Option C.
European Union is an international organization formed to regulate trade relations among member
states.</explanation></answer></answers>