<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Price index is given as Pc/Pb * 100 where Pc is the current year price
and Pb is the base year price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Ans : Option A. Explanation: When tax rate is raised generally, personal income tax will rise.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Transfers are not included because they are not payments on
production activities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The main function of NDIC is to insure bank deposit.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option A. Any borrowing by government either federal, state or local government is
regarded as public debt.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Deflation can be controlled by increasing government spending
more than its revenue as this will lead to more money in circulation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: When bank rate is reduced it will encourage commercial banks to
approach CBN for money thereby increasing money supply.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Rent and Royalties is one of the main sources of government
revenue in Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Ans; Option C. Explanation: Revenue sharing formula is one of the major roles of revenue
mobilization allocation and fiscal commission in Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: When elasticity of demand for a commodity is inelastic the burden is
borne by the consumer since it is easier for the producer to shift it on them.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The existence of close substitute is one of the major determinants of
elasticity of demand. The change in the price of a commodity affects the demand for its
substitute.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The range is obtained by subtracting the lowest figure from the
highest in this case 35 minus 13 equals 22.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option Explanation: Due to the law of diminishing marginal utility a rational consumer will
buy less of X.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Consumer’s demand for goods because of satisfaction they will
derive from consuming it.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Demand for factors of production is derived demand because
factors are demanded for service they will render in production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option C. When indifference curve is a straight line that mean the two goods are not
necessarily combined. Since there is existence of corner solution which implies that on the Y axis
Zero amount of X will be demanded and vice versa.
Y
X
59
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Excess supply arises when there is outward or rightward shift in
supply curve when price and demand are given.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>OptionB. Explanation: As long as the consumer is on the same indifference curve, he
derives the same level of utility with different combination of the two goods.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: The MRS of X and Y is the amount of Y that a consumer is willing to
give up in order to gain additional unit of X and still remain on the same indifference curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B.
+
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The problem of how to produced is a technical issue and has to do
with how factors/input can be combined in order to produce a good.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option B. explanation: Choice is made out of alternative goods due to limited/scarce
resources otherwise, consumer would have demanded every good he want if he has unlimited
resources.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The law of demand relates quantity demand to price. In
mathematical form Qd = f(p) i.e quantity demand depends on price.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The exports of Nigeria comprises mainly primarily product from
agriculture and mining.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Ans : Option D. Explanation: Both the partnership and sole proprietorship has unlimited liability.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Increase in investment will lead to more volume of goods being
produce. This is economic growth.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Floating exchange rate is determined when the forces of demand
and supply interacts.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: When group of people come together to market their products the
association formed is producer cooperative society.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Import substitution is one of measures to correct balance of
payment problem as this will reduce the volume of export.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: UNTAD was established in 1964 with the aim of assisting the
developing countries to solve their balance of payment problem.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Mobility of labour tends to be higher where there are many job
opportunity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option C. Industrialization refers to transformation of economic structure of a country from
primary production to production of industrial goods and services for the purpose of attaining
economic growth and development..
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Most of the oil producing areas in Nigeria are exposed to
environmental pollution in forms of oil spillage, emission of dangerous gas substance into the
air- this provoke agitation for compensation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: standard of living will fall when the dependency ratio is very high;
children and aged constitute dependants.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Epileptic power supply is a major factor militating against
industrialization as most companies would have to incur a huge cost in providing and running
generator.
60
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Minimum wage legislation usually leads to increase in labour supply
since minimum wage is always higher; market determines wage rates.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Oil shock occurs when there is shortage in supply of oil thereby
leading to fuel scarcity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Ans; option B. Explanation: Census is am expensive exercise that requires a huge financial
commitment on the part of government. In Nigeria, financial constraints constitute a serious
problem of conducting census.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Marginal Productivity theory of labour is usually applicable in
perfectly competitive market.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Diminishing returns is associated with short-run per unit COSTCURVES.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Entrepreneur is the most active factor of production because he
organizes, controls and coordinates other factors of production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Ans; Option D. Explanation: In a monopolistic competitive market the price and output decision
of a firm depend on that of other in the industry.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation:
MC cuts AC at its minimum turning point. Thus, MC = AC.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option B.
This is the case of price floor.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option D.
A firm will close down if it cannot cover its average variable cost. The moment its price
falls below average variable cost, it must close down.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option A.
Average product is obtained when the Total Product is divided by the number of labour
input. In this case, when 3 men were employed, total product was 5</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Then, average
product will be 540 divided by 3 which equal 180.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option C.
Average revenue is obtained by dividing total revenue by the number of unit sold. Total
Revenue is price multiplied by the quantity sold. Here, when 6 men were employed,
output is 660. The total revenue will be 13</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Average revenue will be 1320 divided by 6
which equal 220.
</explanation></answer></answers>