<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Efficient allocation of resources is the main thrust of economic
science.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Changes in the prices of shares in stock market are usually caused by
market forcs of demand and supply which is also referred to as invincible hand.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation:
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Standard deviation is one of measures of dispersion others include
mean deviation, range and variance.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Mean is the best known as average and it is not affected by extreme
values in a data.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Because mean is the average of values in a data.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: When elasticity of demand for a good is move elastic than its supply
the burden must be borne by the producer otherwise, there will be loss in revenue as the
consumer may respond greatly to price increases due to tax.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: When a good has elasticity demand and increase in its price will lead
to greater decrease in quantity demanded this will lead to loss of revenue by the producer.
76
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Excess demand of a good can only result in decrease in demand of
the good.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option C. Consumer’s surplus is the difference between what a consumer is willing to pay
for a commodity and what he actually does pay for it. When demand is inelastic change in price
may not necessitate much change in quantity demanded.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Ordinal utility states that utility cannot be measured objectively
rather, consumer can only rank their preference between combinations of two goods.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: The law of diminishing marginal utility has been used to derive the
law of demand which explains the negative slope of a normal demand curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The difference between what a consumer is planning to spend and
the amount he actually spent on it constitute consumer surplus i.e., 120k minus 80k equals 40k.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: A shift in supply curve can only occur when factors affecting supply
other than the price changes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: The supply curve is said to be elastic if the coefficient of price
elasticity of supply is greater than 1.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: A composite supply occurs when two commodities are jointly
supplied. If one product is a by-product of another one, that mean the commodities are jointly
supplied.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: In perfect competitive, price is determined by the interaction of
demand and supply forces and these are referred to as market forces.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Maximum price is used in order to peg down and limit the extent at
which price can be rise. This is price ceiling.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation:
Decreasing returns to scale set in when output increase in less proportion to increase in inputs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Economics of scale occurs when a firm experiences decrease in per
unit cost (average variable cost) as it expands its product on large scale.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: A diseconomies of scale occurs when as a result of increasing output
firm is incurring higher per-unit cost.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: when there is free entry and exit in an industry the supply curve
tend to be elastic.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: In a monopolistic market there is no single seller that dominates the
market.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Demand for factor of production is a derived demand and its slope
downward just as normal demand curve.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Collusion is a situation in which firms in an oligopolistic industry
tactily decide to set the same price as the price leader for the industry.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Level of income is used to determine tax and more so consumption,
savings and investment depends on income.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Economic recession occurs when there is fall in aggregate demand
in an economy
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option D.
Multiplier =
􀬵
􀬵􀬿􀯆􀯉􀮼 􀝔 􀝅􀝊􀝒􀝁􀝏􀝐􀝉􀝁􀝊􀝐
=
􀬵
􀬵􀬿􀬴.􀬻 􀝔 􀜰50􀝉 􀬵
􀬴.􀬷 􀝔 􀜰50􀝉
= N500m
77
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Money as a medium of exchange allows division of labour and
specialization.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Open Market Operation as an instrument of money supply control
by CBN. When CBN buys Treasury bill, it buys with the money from commercial banks; this then
increases money supply to commercial banks and the economy at large.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C.
Velocity of money refers to the speed at which money circulates within the economy by
changing from one hand to another. When there is an increase in velocity of money in
circulation, prices will increase thus leading to lower value of money.
MV = PT
where M = money supply;
V = velocity of money;
P = price level;
T = quantity of goods
PT = real gross domestic product.
V = 􀯉􀯍
􀯆
; ∴ V = 􀯥􀯘􀯔􀯟 􀯀􀮽􀯉
􀯆􀯢􀯡􀯘􀯬 􀯌􀯨􀯣􀯣􀯟􀯬
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: An important function of commercial bank is granting of loans to
customers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: To curb unemployment using fiscal policy government will increase
spending and decrease its taxes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: When government borrows to finance its expenses it embarks on
deficit budget.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Most of Nigeria development plans are adequate and robust but
problem lies in the implementation strategies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Ans; Option A. Explanation; Food sufficiency is the major aim of Nigeria Agricultural policies.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Granting of subsidy is a government policy aimed at reducing the
selling price of commodity. Subsidy granted on farm input will help to reduce the production
cost of farmers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Localization means concentration of industries in a particular area.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A. Explanation: Locomotion of even development is one of the tenets of LDC.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: Poor maintenance of the refineries
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option A. explanation: By definition and act of parliament, the ultimate aim of every
producer is to make profit.`
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option D.
􀬶􀬴􀬴􀬷 􀯣􀯢􀯣􀯨􀯟􀯔􀯧􀯜􀯢􀯡􀬿􀬶􀬴􀬴􀬶 􀯣􀯢􀯣􀯨􀯟􀯔􀯧􀯜􀯢􀯡
􀬶􀬴􀬴􀬶 􀯣􀯢􀯣􀯨􀯟􀯔􀯧􀯜􀯢􀯡 􀝔 100% = 􀬺􀬴􀬿􀬸􀬴
􀬸􀬴 􀝔100% 􀵌 50%
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option D.
􀬶􀬴􀬴􀬶 􀯪􀯢􀯥􀯞􀯜􀯡􀯚 􀯣􀯢􀯣􀯨􀯟􀯔􀯧􀯜􀯢􀯡
􀬶􀬴􀬴􀬶 􀯧􀯢􀯧􀯔􀯟 􀯣􀯢􀯣􀯨􀯟􀯔􀯧􀯜􀯢􀯡 􀝔 100%
= 􀬷􀬶
􀬸􀬴 􀝔 100% 􀵌 80%
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option D. Explanation: one of the characteristics of free trade countries is the
harmonization of trade among member countries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: Japan receives payment on her export which will appear as credit.
78
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Promotion of economic and social development is one of the
objectives of ADB (Africa Development Bank).
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option B. Explanation: The level of technical knowhow of a country goes a long way in
determining the method of production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option C. Explanation: Marginal productivity of labour is defined as the change in total
output resulting from employing additional unit of labour.</explanation></answer></answers>