<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option C
Type red as indicated on the question paper.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option D
The linear scale is 1cm to 1km i.e. 1:100000.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option D
The highest contour is inland while the lowest is outside.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A
Reason: Presence of farmsteads in the map area.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C
Most settlements are in the lowland region in the North.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option A
The length is multiplied by the non-constant part of the scale i.e. 5 × 50000cm = 250000cm or
2.5km.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option D
􀬸􀬷􀬺􀬴
􀬸􀬶􀬹􀬴􀬴 􀵈 􀬵􀬴􀬴
􀬵 % 􀵌 10.25882% 􀵌 11.26%.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option B
Measure the angle with a protractor.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B
There is no major obstruction that reduces or aid to measurement on plains.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option B
Silica and aluminium; this is because the earth’s crust is also called SIAL.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option B
Sandstone is formed from the deposition of eroded rock particles of varying sizes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option D
Basalt is an extrusive igneous rock seen physically on the earth surface.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option C
Sedimentary rocks are derived rocks formed by the accumulation of deposited materials
composed of previously existing rocks or organic materials.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option B
Barrier reefs are formed when coral deposits are cemented together usually close the
continental shelves.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option C
They are the shallowest part of (the) oceans close to the land where most fishing is carried out.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option C
Ox-bow Lake is a feature associated with the lower course or the plains stage of a river.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option A
Change in direction of wave front is associated with refraction.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option C
Typhoon is a violent tropical cyclone which occurs mainly over the China Sea.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option D
Tropical continental climate is associated with alternate marked dry and wet seasons
throughout the year.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option D
Xerophytes can survive in dry habitats because it stores water in its stem and has no leaf. It only
has thorns in place of leaf thereby reducing evapo-transpiration.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option C
Leached oxides are deposited in the B horizon thereby resulting in its accumulation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option C
Sand, silt and clay particles determine the makeup or texture of the soil.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option C
Ocean water is mainly used as inter-continental route ways linking the continents apart from air.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option A
Terrestrial ecosystems are called biomes i.e. biological belts (where living organisms live).
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option A
Global warming results in ice melting which then flows into the sea and increases the level of
water.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option D
Intensive cultivation and overgrazing leads to deforestation which exposes the soil to erosion.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option B
Frozen soil is not conducive to human habitation because it discourages farming and it is very
inclement for man and animals.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option A
It is the ratio of registered births to the proportion of women of child-bearing age.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B
The no. of deaths, births, immigrants and emigrants over a specified time interval determines
population change.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option C
Holiday resort is associated with relaxation which is the hallmark of tourism.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option C
Conurbation is the merging of two or more urban areas but when the urban centres are big
cities, they are called MEGALOPOLIS.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C
This is due to the prevalence of agricultural activities over a large expanse of land.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option D
The basic goal of an entrepreneur is profit-maximization. So, he locates where this can be best
achieved.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option D
Inequality accounts for inability to either produce or buy food for self & other dependants.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option A
Railway transport is the commonest means of transportation in the developed economics of
Europe and North America.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option B
The developed countries are leading manufacturer of products and importer of raw materials.
They are thus engaged in trading activities more than the others.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option C
Brass, bronze works, wooden masks etc are locally produced by craftsmen.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option A
Petroleum being a liquid is mostly drilled and evacuated via pipelines.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option B
These products are produced mainly in the South where the conditions for their growth exist.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A
The Eastern scarp land attains the general height of 300-400m above sea level.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option A
They are methods of over-coming agricultural problems of erosion, irregular rainfall and use of
traditional/crude methods and implements.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option D
People migrate to Lagos area in search of employment mainly and wide market of products.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option C
Differences in climatic conditions and soils favour the growth of different crops in the different
regions.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option C
The great East African rift valley is reputed to be the largest in the world.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option A
Sahel region is a pseudo desert land.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option A
Hassi Messaous is known for petroleum mining in Algeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option B
People of West Africa avoid the Northern parts due to the presence of the Sahel Zone and
Southern fringe of Sahara desert while they congregate in the South where the soils and other
factors are favourable.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option C
Kilimanjaro is in Kenya close to its border with Tanzania.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option A
Cocoa is widely produced in small plantations across West Africa while Coffee is in East Africa
because of its hilly nature.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option C
The Nile valley and delta is a age-long heavily populated </explanation></answer></answers>