<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B.
This is because rivers usually flow through valleys and the symbol below represents embankment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C.
This is because the length is 6.75cm and the scale is 1cm to 2km. Therefore, length is 2km x 6.75 =
13.5km.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option D.
There are scattered cultivations all over the map area.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option A.
The feature marked Y is an Ox-bow lake. It is also known as cut-offs or bayous. It is a feature of
lower course. In the lower course, the meander becomes pronounced. There will come a time when
the river cuts through the narrow neck of the loop.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C.
River Haba develops a winding course. The irregularities of the ground forced the river to swing in
loops, forming meanders.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option D.
Prismatic compass can be used to obtain bearings of features. The bearing of each line is
determined independently in that any error can be confirmed.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option D.
Petroleum industry covers 172.8o of the total i.e.,
􀬵􀬻􀬶.􀬼
􀬷􀬺􀬴
x 25000 = 12,000.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option D.
Iron and steel cover 115.2o of the total number of workers i.e., 􀬵􀬵􀬹.􀬶
􀬷􀬺􀬴
= 0.32.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option D.
Station M is due West and in bearing reading normally begins from due North. This means places
due East will be 90o due South 180o and due West 270o.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option B.
It is the biggest lake in Africa and River Nile flows out of the lake.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option C.
The lakes occupy the great East African rift valley.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option A.
It is due to the subsidence of air masses which makes annual rainfall along the coast of Kenya to be
less than expected of an equatorial region.
The warm Mozambique current is a bit far from the Kenyan coast while the Monsoon drift flows
towards the Indian sub-continent thus leaving Kenya without major warm current.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option A.
Kano was a Caravan terminus during the era of Trans-Sahara Trade of 18th Century. Thus, its early
religious and economic significance accounts for its being a major population centre.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option A.
The region is in the equatorial part of Sudan with good soils and rivers Bahr-el-Ghaza and while Nile
watering the area. This enables different fauna and flora to flourish.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option B.
The prevailing wind indicated is the North-East trade wind which covers the country most effectively
from November to March.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option D.
The shaded area covers parts of forest belt, fresh water swamp and Guinea savanna; the total
annual rainfall ranges from 101cm and 200cm.
i.e., the shaded area is the tropical hinterland climate zone whose annual rainfall is 101cm – 200cm.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option B.
The ferralitic soil is the heavily leached forest soil.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option D.
The towns in the Niger Delta which are rich in petroleum deposits and their coastal location leads to
their development as oil terminals.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option A.
Enugu and Jos are very important sources of coal, tin and columbite respectively. Eastern railway
line was attracted to evacuate the minerals. Similarly, Kaduna and Minna are important termini on
the Western railway line.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C.
Mozambique and Natal have conditions that favour sugar cane production – rivers and good soil as
well as the presence of the AFRICAN/Boer tribes in South Africa.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option A.
Liberia is Africa’s leading producer of rubber which is produced from plantations. Rubber serves as
raw material for the cornerstone rubber industry.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D.
There is no month without rainfall and the highest rainfall figure (heaviest) occurs in September –
October.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option A.
The climatic data is that of Warri in Nigeria. The data shows that there is no month without rain.
Warri is located on the deltaic plain not far from the Atlantic Ocean.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option A.
Nigeria is not a major producer of Iron ore while the country does not produce bauxite and diamond
at all.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option B.
Cattle ranching is prominent in the Obudu Plateau; it is well-developed as tourists attraction centre
in Cross river in Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option A.
Eurasian Tundra is situated in the extremely cold climate that does not support high population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option C.
Dairying is an agro-allied industry which enables milk, cheese, etc, to be packaged for man.
Dairying products are perishable. Thus, they are required in high demand which can be met by
practising them around large cities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option D.
Japan is endowed with large pool of skilled manpower. It is noted for low cost of production and
hence cheapness of the goods. Japan is recognized for high technological proficiency.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B.
People move mostly from rural to urban areas and where they move from rural to rural, it is often
due to pressure on resources and inadequate employment opportunities.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option D.
The seasonal fluctuation in the levels of water can be overcome by constructing dams, locks and
canals.
Locks and canals increase water volume by helping to build up water body and diverting water from
other rivers into the one needing more water.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option D.
USA and England have extensive conurbations as a result of industrialization and close affinity
between the two countries – Industrial Eastern seaboard of USA and midlands of England.
The Chicago conurbation is a merger between Chicago and Gary. New York, Jersey City, Newark and
Patterson have merged to form a conurbation in North-East of USA. Also, midland of England-
Birmingham-Walsal-Oldbury has merged to a conurbation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C.
Textile and footwear industries are labour intensive. Thus, abundant cheap labour is very important
in locating the industries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option B.
Birth rate is measured per thousand of the total population per annum
Therefore, the birth rate
= 1000 2%
150,000,000
3,000,000 × =
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option A.
Efficient inland transportation is needed in bringing raw materials as well as distributing finished
products of the industries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option D.
The relaxation of currency control would ensure more money in the circulation. This will encourage
massive importation of goods into a country.
Relaxation of currency control will lead to a fall in the value of a nation’s currency in comparison to
the major currencies thus encouraging high importation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option A.
Low birth and death rates are uncommon phenomena in population pyramid. They rarely go
together.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option A.
Forest reservation will go a long way to prevent water shed degradation. Preventing or discouraging
deforestation around the water shed will do the work.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option A.
All warm currents originate from the highly warm waters of the equatorial regions where the high,
constant temperature ensures that the water remain warm.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D.
Most of the monsoon forests yield valuable timber and are prized for their durable hardwoods. Teak
is the best known among those hardwoods. Burma alone accounts for as much as three-quarters of
the World’s production.
Teak is a tree that is associated with Monsoon forest in Asia.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option D.
Non-renewable resources took millions of years to form below the earth’s surface and once used up
they are lost forever e.g. mineral.
Mineral cannot be renewed since it is not a self-sustaining resource like water forest.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option B.
The period covers the solstices between the spring and autumnal equinoxes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option A.
Contouring prevents easy flow of water and reduces the speed of down-slope water movement.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option D.
Remains of swamps and forests are embedded in the sediments. The pressure of overlying
sediments compresses it into compact masses of carbon which eventually become lignite or coal.
Lignite is the earliest form of coal which is a carbonaceous organically formed rock.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option B.
Monsoon climates are typically single maximum belt or zone; thus, the high temperature signifies its
tropical location.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option A.
The basement complex is made up of very old and stable rocks which were formed over 1,500
million years ago.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option C.
An organism needs to adapt to the prevailing conditions before it could survive in a natural
ecosystem. All organisms have enemies capable of shortening their life-span but adaptability
ensures their survival.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option A.
Delta is formed in locations where deposits are not swept off by strong tides. The formation of a
delta depends on the rate of sedimentation, the depth of the river and sea-bed, the character of the
tides, currents and waves.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option D.
Texture refers to the size of individual particles making up the soil (light or heavy soils). Structure is
the grouping of soil particles into clusters or aggregates of different sizes and shapes e.g. platty,
blocky, prismatic or granular.
Porosity is associated with the pore spaces between soil particles.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option C.
It is a stack. It is formed when a headland is attacked from both sides by waves. The waves can
succeed in cutting through thereby forming an arch. If the roof of an arch collapses, a piece of rock
called stack is left standing in the sea.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option B.A stack is one of the landforms produced by wave erosion. Wave erosion is a powerful agent of
erosion in coastal areas.</explanation></answer></answers>