<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option A.
The map covers an area of 17.5cm by 12cm and has a scale of 1cm to represent 2km.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C.
Reason: Presence of mineral workings in the North-West of Chokali.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option B.
Gradient is VI
HE
and Zafi is approximately on 925m while the bridge is 740m meaning that the VI =
185m.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option D.
The settlements are far apart.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C.
They are both located on lower land compared to the trig. station.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option B.
It has a single maximum rainfall and high temperature pattern.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option A.
Range = highest temperature minus lowest temperature.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option A.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option A.
Similarities in areas where obstacles occur enables the surveyor to take measurement of the
unobstructed places in place of the obstructed places.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option B.
Linear scale is the relationship between features shown on maps and the actual feature on the
ground.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option A.
The Volta Dam project was carried out to provide electricity and water for irrigation.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option C.
They are two major towns apart from Accra that has coastal locations.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option B.
Atlas Mount is found close to the coast of Morocco in North Africa.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option A.
Enugu is a town whose growth is due to the mining of coal from the Udi escarpment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option C.
Oil Palm belt is largely in the Southern part of Nigeria which roughly corresponds to the forest6
region.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option A.
Oil palm plantations and the old species which grow naturally are the main sources of production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option D.
They are among the millionaire cities in Africa and most of them pull people from their hinterlands.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option D.
Most inselbergs are found in the Western and Northern areas of the country where the basement
complex rocks are found.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option B.
High population leads to high demand for land as a factor of production resulting in high pressure.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C.
Senegal is in the Sahelian zone with sparse rainfall and sandy soil which favours groundnut
production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option A.
Petroleum industry is the leading supplier of foreign exchange and also large employer of labour in
Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D.
Jos Plateau is a major watershed in Northern Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option D.
Temperate and sub-tropical grassland is otherwise called VELDT in South Africa with modified
temperate characteristics.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option C.
The feature shows the peel-off surface typical of exfoliation domes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option A.
Exfoliation is due to alternate wetting and drying found mainly in the tropical region.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option B.
Low pressure is associated with areas with high temperature.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option D.
Carbon(IV) oxide is the waste product used by green plants during photosynthesis.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option C.
Water, plants and soil are continuous-flow items i.e., items that naturally replace selves as soon as
the existing ones are used.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option D.
Climax is the state referring to the utmost level of attainment reached naturally due to continuous
growth.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option C.
Definite arrangement of soil particles makes them shiny.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option B.
Cool ocean currents usually originate from the high latitudes which are usually cold and flow
towards the equator thus bringing coolness and dry conditions.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option A.
The rock is batholiths which is a massive dome found beneath the earth’s surface (where volcanic
eruption had taken place).
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option B.
Limestone is associated with joints and bedding planes which encourages the development of
sinkholes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option A.
Needle leaves are designed to reduce evapo-transpiration while the soft woods are associated with
temperate conditions.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option D.
The earth rotates 15o in one hour and therefore, 1o in 4 minutes.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option B.
Alteration will disrupt the existing relationship.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option C.
The leveling up of or erosion of a large area to reduce it to peneplain results in the formation of
residual hills called monadnock.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option B.
Rotation of the earth leads to a deflection of tides and currents. This is due to Ferrell’s Law.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option A.
Latosol is formed by wind drift whereby a layer resistant to erosion will attract more deposition of
wind-carried materials.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option B.
Japan is prone to earthquakes because it is in the Pacific belt of fire.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option D.
Land produces plants which use up carbon(IV) oxide and release oxygen into the atmosphere.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option D.
Rainfall is the major determinant of plants’ growth.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option A.
The size of settlements depend on their population And the functions they perform Are dependent
on the people in them.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option D.
They are the most industrialized; they possess a higher standard of living making air transportation
affordable to the citizens.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option A.
The West coast of South Africa is partly due to the cold Benguela current and the Namib desert in
the area.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option B.
Cities joined together with each still maintaining its identity are called megalopolis.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option A.
Terylene is made from the waste products of the petroleum industry among which are poly
products.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option D.
Migration changes the distribution pattern of population.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option B.
The Ruhr region is found mainly in Germany in the Valley of Ruhr River.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option A.
Commonwealth countries refer to countries formerly colonized by Great Britain most of which still
has attachment to Britain.
</explanation></answer></answers>