<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option D.
Rice: This is because the area is liable to flooding and rice needs a lot of water to perform well.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C.
Ridge: This is because the contour lines are close together and the feature itself is elongated.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option C.
6.5Km is the distance on a straight line.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option B.
Lumbering – presence of thick forest.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C.
320m – The peak (highest point) on the ridge which is also the highest area on the map.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option A.
16% - This is because cocoa represents 58o of the total angle in the pie-chart i.e.,
􀬹􀬼
􀬷􀬺􀬴
x 100% = 16.1% 􀘆 16%.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option C.
In the pie chart, the tree crop comprises cocoa and oil palm and has the %:
100% 36%
360
130 × ≅ o
o
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option D.
Fixed obstacles are best dealt with by laying offsets i.e., measuring the perpendicular distances to
the particular obstacle at intervals from the chain line.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B.
Ground survey aims to make an accurate map of a part of the earth’s surface.
Dot map is very widely used for showing distribution e.g. population. It is used to show absolute
figures e.g. a dot may represent 2,000 people on the map.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option A.
Make an accurate map of a part of the earth’s surface – survey can only show just a little part of the
earth’s large surface and since accurate instruments are used in surveying, the map that will be
drawn will be accurate.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option B.
This is because accurate measurements can only be got when the surface is plane and not when it is
sloping, oblique or bumpy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option A.
This is because bees and butterflies are agents of pollination whose basic pre-occupation is
collection of nectar from flowers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option D.
When the masses of debris are deposited at the foot of the hill or the mouth of the valley in the
desert, an alluvial fan is formed.
Streams in such places flow sluggishly and as such, deposits lots of the sand blown into it by wind.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option D.
The prairie of North America is recognized for Wheat production. Wheat is best supported by
temperate climate. In other words, they are temperate grasslands.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option D.
To enable the thermometer have an accurate temperature reading and avoid radiation. It is raised
1.2metres above the ground to avoid the heat from the ground.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option A.
Wind – It influences both rainfall and temperature; it is itself one of the elements of weather and
climate.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option D.
The destruction of their habitat exposes the animals to both human poachers and natural destroyers
like cold, etcetera.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option C.
Coal is formed from carbonaceous plants changed from its original form during thermodynamic
processes. It is formed when the pressure of overlying sediments compress the plant remains into
compact masses of carbon.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option B.
The ozone layer had been found to be absorbent to the destructive ultra-violet rays and their
depletion means more and more of the rays reach the earth’s surface. Ozone layer is naturally
designed to absorb harmful rays; its depletion automatically leads to introduction of ultra violet rays
into the troposphere.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option A.
This is because only cirque is an erosion landform of glaciations. Others are not. A cirque is produced
by glacial erosion. It is a depression where névé accumulates.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option B.
Only profile is not a characteristic of soil and it is also the only option that exhibits different rock
types.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D.
This is because the longitudes are on either sides of the Prime Meridian and as such had to be added
to get the longitude difference. Longitude difference = 35o + 25o = 60o
hrs 4 hrs
15
Time Difference 60o
o
= =
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option C.
High temperature and rainfall are characteristics of equatorial climate and Democratic Republic of
Congo, Brazil and Indonesia lie in the equatorial region.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option D.
Location in the desert results in high evaporation and since surface rivers do not flow into it, no
dilution of the shrunk water occurs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option D.
Only granite possesses distinct grains of mica that are resistant to erosion among the office
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option C.
The earth, moon and sun can only be on a straight line due to earth’s rotation and tides and ocean
currents are due to rotation of the earth.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option D.
Textile industry requires cotton, flax, silk and wool as the basic raw materials for its production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option B.
Ghana produces more than countries in the other options given. Ghana produces over 30% of
World’s Cocoa. Nigeria produces about 20% and Brazil produces about 30%.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B.
Prices of unprocessed agricultural products are not stable in the world market. The developing
countries suffer a great loss to unstable price of their exporting crops at the world market.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option A.
Both regions are highly developed economically and technologically. They represent the root of
industrial revolution.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option B.
280,000 in 1980 and 210,000 in 1975 implies 70,000 increase in 5 years.
Thus we have:
􀬻􀬴,􀬴􀬴􀬴
􀬶􀬵􀬴,􀬴􀬴􀬴
x 100% 􀵊 5 = 􀬵
􀬷 􀵈 􀬵􀬴􀬴
􀬹 􀵌 􀬶􀬴
􀬷 % = 6.7%
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option B.
Lagos is a commercial centre in Nigeria and San Francisco is a coastal settlement in North America.
Each of the two settlements by virtue of their coastal location has a seaport and an international
airport.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option C.
The young able-bodied men usually embark on migration for better economic opportunities. Thus,
there will be more females than males in the source areas.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option D.
They are major OPEC members and are largely mono-economic nations. The World oil producing
countries include Nigeria, Qatar, Kuwait and Saudi Arabia.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option A.
Conurbation represents the merger of two or more cities with each maintaining its identity.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option A.
This is because the parts are imported from advanced countries and assembled in West Africa.
Peugeot Assembly Plant in Kaduna, Nigeria in West Africa is a good example.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option B.
People in villages engage in extractive activities like farming, fishing, lumbering, mining, etc. Villages
are mostly nucleated and compact in nature. They are often a focus of transport arteries for the
inflow and outflow of goods and services.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option D.
Mahogany, Obeche, Iroko, etc, are hard woods which can resist early decay. They are tropical
hardwoods suitable for the construction of railway steepers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option D.
The shape and direction of the shoreline ensure that most wind blow off-shore leading to dryness.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A.
The route-ways (road, rail, water) need constant maintenance and the facilities (seaports, airports)
as well as the spare parts which are costly to acquire and maintain.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option C.
Zambia has one of the world’s largest reserves of copper. Copper accounts for more than 97% of
Zambia’s export value. The Zambia copper belt is an extension of the Shaba Copper belt of
Democratic Republic of Congo.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option C.
Rapid growth of urban centres in tropical Africa is largely due to rural-urban migration as the young
school leavers move to the cities in search of jobs.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option C.
Bush burning has become an incessant seasonal problem facing Savanna vegetation and so militates
against the development of Climax vegetation in the savanna belt of Nigeria.
People in the Savannah belt of Nigeria destroy the bushes annually while trying to kill games animals
by setting them on fire.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option A.
Jos plateau and Mambilla Plateau modify the local climate which makes the climate relatively cooler
than it is least expected. This climatic condition favours the growth of wheat.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option C.
Atlas Mountain of Morocco in North Africa and Cape ranges of West Africa are good examples of
Fold Mountains in Africa.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option D.
Cairo is the second largest city, after Johannesburg, in Africa. The Lower Nile valley in Cairo is one of
the densely populated areas of the world.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option B.
Udi hill is the same as Enugu Escarpment and is an example of Cuesta landscape in Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option B.
The Industrial smokes constitute the major air pollution around Nkalagu and Ewekoro in Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option C.
Nigeria is Africa’s largest producer of Petroleum which also has a large natural gas deposit and the
ECOWAS Treaty opens the West African market to Nigeria. Nigeria has agreed to supply petroleum
products and gas to some West African countries e.g. Ghana, Rep. of Benin etc.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option C.
The East African Rift valley system is 4800km long, stretching from East Africa through the Red Sea
to Syria. It contains the following lakes: Lake Tangay</explanation></answer></answers>