<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<answers><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>1</ano><explanation>Option B
Reason: Presence of scattered cultivations.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>2</ano><explanation>Option C
Settlement avoids highland regions preferring the valleys.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>3</ano><explanation>Option D
The spot height has automatically fixed height.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>4</ano><explanation>Option B
Hills dominate the map area making the region rugged.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>5</ano><explanation>Option C
The contour lines are close together and elongated.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>6</ano><explanation>Option C
When reducing, the scale of the map is multiplied by the inverted size of reduction.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>7</ano><explanation>Option C
The cattle produced is 40%.
i.e. 􀬸􀬴
􀬵􀬴􀬴 􀵈 􀬺,􀬴􀬴􀬴,􀬴􀬴􀬴
􀬵
􀵌 60,000 􀵈 40
􀵌 2,400,000.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>8</ano><explanation>Option B
Pigs (5%), Camels (10%) and Donkey (10%) Addition = 25%
i.e. 􀬶􀬹
􀬵􀬴􀬴 􀵈 􀬶,􀬸􀬴􀬴,􀬴􀬴􀬴
􀬵
i.e. 1,500,000.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>9</ano><explanation>Option B
Optical Square is used in setting out right angles in surveying.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>10</ano><explanation>Option A
Equator and all lines of longitude form complete circle otherwise called Great circles.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>11</ano><explanation>Option A
Slate is the metamorphic form of shale.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>12</ano><explanation>Option D
Sandstone is classified as arenaceous because it is formed from eroded rock particles of varying
grains.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>13</ano><explanation>Option D
Karst windows is formed when underground caves is formed.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>14</ano><explanation>Option D
Interlocking spurs and meanders are associated with middle course of rivers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>15</ano><explanation>Option C
Carbonation is a chemical process where carbon is the catalyst resulting in the breakdown of
rocks.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>16</ano><explanation>Option B
When prevailing winds are on-shore, the properties of the ocean currents are carried by the
wind on-shore.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>17</ano><explanation>Option D
Wind vane or weather cock is the instrument used in measuring wind direction.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>18</ano><explanation>Option C
Tropical humid climate has a fairly distributed high rainfall all year round and constantly high
temp.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>19</ano><explanation>Option B
Coniferous forest has needle – shed leaves and leaf droppings are few. This exposes the soil to
intense sunshine.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>20</ano><explanation>Option C
Water logging results when soil can no longer absorb water making it marshy.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>21</ano><explanation>Option A
Matured soil is associated with different zones and is therefore called ZONAL SOIL.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>22</ano><explanation>Option D
Nuclear energy is generated from natures continuous flow (from the natural resources fed unto
it) i.e. processed uranium.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>23</ano><explanation>Option A
Pollutant influences the environment negatively – it poisons the flora and fauna in an
environment.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>24</ano><explanation>Option C
Hurricane is one of the strong tropical storms. It is natural.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>25</ano><explanation>Option B
Nile basin is a long-standing irrigation-propelled productive land. This encourages high
population of farmers.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>26</ano><explanation>Option A
South-East Asia is agriculturally productive and is an emerging industrial region with countries
like China, Korea, Malaysia etc.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>27</ano><explanation>Option D
The developed countries had adopted birth-control measures which are now reflected by lowbirth
rate and the highly developed health facilities lead to low death rate.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>28</ano><explanation>Option C
Urban settlements are engaged in tertiary activities like trading, banking etc and other services.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>29</ano><explanation>Option B
They are important seaports in their respective countries.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>30</ano><explanation>Option A
The descending order in terms of complexity of functions means arrangement of settlements
from the biggest to the smallest.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>31</ano><explanation>Option C
All the activities involve exploitation of natural resources.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>32</ano><explanation>Option C
Forward linkage is a process whereby an enterprise produces goods which serves as raw
material for another industry.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>33</ano><explanation>Option B
Most less-developed nations import more goods than they export.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>34</ano><explanation>Option C
The grasslands (temperate) of North and South America as well as that of Russia are known
wheat-growing areas.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>35</ano><explanation>Option B
Rubber production is very common in the countries of their tropical nature which favours
rubber.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>36</ano><explanation>Option A
The Rhine industrial region is connected to other European regions by network of canals used as
waterways.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>37</ano><explanation>Option D
Western Europe has a population of people who cherishes fruit diets than African most of whom
prefer carbohydrates.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>38</ano><explanation>Option C
The subsistence nature of our agriculture makes cultivation to be low. Inadequacy of funds
compounds the problem.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>39</ano><explanation>Option C
Kano is a hinter land city and boat-building needs coastal location.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>40</ano><explanation>Option A
Bays and headlands are found along sea and ocean coasts.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>41</ano><explanation>Option C
The cities are at the centre of groundnut producing areas.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>42</ano><explanation>Option B
Termini are settlement where railway begins orents. Kaura Namoda marks the western end of
the western railways in the North-West while Nguru is the terminus in the North East.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>43</ano><explanation>Option B
The middle belt region is known for its agricultural production – large - scale tuber and grain
production.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>b</canswer><ano>44</ano><explanation>Option B
Western uplands dominate the relief of Western Nigeria.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>45</ano><explanation>Option C
Adamawa highlands dominate the shaded area - below the Benue rover in the Middle belt.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>46</ano><explanation>Option C
The variation in the relief of east Africa makes different parts of the region to favour different
crops.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>a</canswer><ano>47</ano><explanation>Option A
Landlocked countries are found hinterland having no coastal boundary.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>c</canswer><ano>48</ano><explanation>Option C
The great East Africa riff Valley dominates East African landscape.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>49</ano><explanation>Option D
Kariba Lake is formed by the dam on River Zambezi.
</explanation></answer><answer><canswer>d</canswer><ano>50</ano><explanation>Option D
Cote D’Ivoire is virtually in the same climatic and political region with Ghana, Nigeria etc but due
to excellent organization, there is improved agricultural production that is found in the other
West African Countries.</explanation></answer></answers>